对于已经登录的用户，
For folks already signed in,
好奇你在 traps 实验的经历。
curiosity how you experience being with the traps lab.
如果你已经开始了懒分配实验，进展如何。
If you already started on the lazy allocation lab, how's that going.
[]是不是比页表实验轻松。
[] that was was less painful than the page table lab.
Andrew You ，你有什么想说的吗？
Andrew You, you want to say something about that.
我认为 traps 实验没问题，
I thought the traps lab was OK,
我只是想确认一下，
It was just making sure that
我使用 trampoline 页面有点烦人。
I actually use the trampoline page properly was a little annoying.
是的。
Yep.
但是一旦我弄清楚了，然后它就可以工作了。
But once I figured that out, then then it just kind of worked.
好的，是的，实验的整个目标是，
Good good, yeah, the whole goal was lab [],
把 trap 处理入口和出口完全暴露给你。
you really expose you to the trap handling entry and exit.
Amir 呢，你在 traps 实验的经历如何。
How about Amir, how was your experience with the traps lab.
我觉得 traps 实验很好，比页表实验易于管理。
I thought that traps lab was good, very much more manageable than the page table lab.
我注意到有机会更精巧地实现的某些方面，这很好，这真是太好了
I noticed that there were like opportunities to be clever about some aspects of the implementation, which was nice
到目前为止，懒分配实验的调试情况还不错。
and lazy lab is good so far debugging.
但在我看来，两者都比页表要好。
But both better than the page table in my opinion.
很高兴听到你这么说，
Glad to hear that,
我相信你也很高兴听到这个，
I'm sure you were glad to hear that,
但我也很高兴听到你这么说。
but I'm glad to hear it too.
Timmy 怎么样？
How about Timmy []?
是的，前两个实验比页表要好得多。
Yeah, these two previous labs have been a lot better than the page table.
我想，对于懒分配实验来说最难的是，
I guess, the hardest part for the lazy lab, the lazy one
读写和所有的东西，
was the read and write and all that stuff,
但在我看来并不是那么糟糕。
but it's not it's not that bad in my opinion.
好的。
Okay.
Catherine 怎么样，
How do Catherine,
对你来说， traps 实验或懒分配实验与页表实验相比较。
was the traps lab or the lazy lab for you in comparison to the page table lab.
你在吗，Katherine ， Katherine Weeks 。
Are you there, Katherine, Katherine Weeks.
你好，我做得很好，
Hello, I'm doing well,
抱歉，我不知道你在跟哪个 Catherine 说话，
sorry I didn't know which Catherine you're talking to,
我想大概只有 20 个人，
I guess there's only twenty people,
所以你可能不太可能还有另一个。
so you're probably not likely that there's another one.
我做得很好。
I'm doing quite well.
很好，所以这个实验比页表实验少了很多痛苦.
Good good, so this lab is less painful than the pagetable lab or.
是的，绝对不会那么痛苦。
Yeah, it's definitely less painful.
太棒了。
Excellent.
嗯。
Yeah.
页表后面的那个 traps （实验），绝对简单的多。
The the one the one after page tables, what was that traps, that was definitely much simpler.
好的，很高兴听到你们这么说，
OK great, we're glad to hear that,
我只想做个非正式的民意测验，
I just wanted to get an informal poll see,
页表实验比我们预想的要难，
you know the page table turned out harder than we thought it would,
所以，这些更好。
and so, like you know these ones are better.
好的，那么我们要做什么呢。
OK, so what do we get going.
不管你在哪里，欢迎收看 6.S081 的下一节课，
And welcome to the next lecture in 6.S081 wherever you are,
今天的主题是关于中断，
so the topic in today is about interrupts,
在开始讨论中断之前，
before jumping into sort of talking about interrupts,
我想分享一点东西，
I wanted to share a little bit one thing,
我想说的是，
that I wanted to talk about,
上个星期，我没能抽出时间来做这件事。
last week which I didn't get around do it through.
你可能会感兴趣的。
And you know what you might find interesting.
让我看下，在这里找到我正确的屏幕，
Let me see, if I can get my right screen here up,
所以在这里，看我屏幕的左下角，
so here, you know you see my screen here on the bottom left,
我通过对话机登录到 Athena 。
I'm actually logged into Athena through the dialogue machines.
我有几件事想谈谈，
And there's a couple things I wanted to talk about,
在真正的操作系统中，内存是如何使用的。
in terms of how memory is being used by a real operating system.
因为我们上周谈了很多，特别是在课程的最后，
Since we talked a lot about that last week, particularly the end of the lecture,
很多问题关于逐出页面，寻找空闲内存之类的东西。
a lot of questions about, you know page out, finding free memory and all that kind of stuff.
这是一台 Athena 机器，
So this is one of Athena machines,
你要注意的是，
you're wanting to note,
如果你看一下内存这一行，它告诉你有多少，
if you look at the memory line, it actually tells you how much,
运行的程序是 top ，可能你们很多人都用过它，
the program running is called top, probably many of you have used it,
你可以看到一台机器里有多少内存，
you see how much machine memories in a machine
如你所见，这台机器里有很多内存。
as you can see, there's a quite a bit of memory in in this machine.
如果你仔细看一下，实际上大部分都是在使用的。
And if you look a little bit carefully, actually most of it is used, right.
很大一部分内存实际上并没有被应用程序使用，
The you know, a large part of the memory is actually not being used by applications,
而是由缓冲器高速缓存使用。
but actually used by the buffer cache.
这在操作系统中很常见，
I said this is quite common in an operating system,
你不想让你的内存无所事事，
you don't really want to leave your physical memory, sitting idle and do nothing,
你可能把它用在有用的东西上，
you might as well use it for something useful,
在这种情况下，它的很大一部分用于缓冲区缓存。
and so in this case, use a good chunk of it is actually used for a buffer cache.
一些内存是空闲的，不是很多，
A little bit of memory, free, not much,
在一台机器中总内存的一小部分，
you know fraction of the total memory that actually in a machine
这是一个非常常见的情况，像大多数操作系统一样。
and so this is a very common case, like most operating systems run.
我们在任何时刻都几乎没有可用的内存。
We basically almost no memory free at any particular instant in time.
这意味着，如果应用程序或内核需要一些内存，
And so that means, for example, if an application or the kernel needs some memory
我们得扔掉一些东西，
and we'll have to throw out something,
也许这几页就足够了，
you know, maybe that's enough for a few pages where a handful of pages,
但在某种情况下，它需要大量的空闲内存，
but at some point it needs a lot of free memory,
它会要求从应用程序或缓冲器告诉缓存中中逐出某些内容。
it will ask to evict something either from the applications or from the buffer cache.
所以这里的主要观点是，
And so you know sort of the main point here basically is that here,
当内核分配内存时，
when the kernel makes allocate memory,
通常不是一个便宜的操作，
it's actually not generally not a cheap operation,
因为没有太多空闲内存可用。
because the memory is not, there's not a ton of memory free available.
另一件有趣的事情是，
The other thing that's sort of interesting to look at is
我根据驻留内存量对 top 的输出进行排序。
I sorted the output of top by the amount of resident memory.
所以你看的每一行，
So you're looking at every line,
对于每个进程，这是地址空间的大小，
for every process you see that, this is size of address space
然后，下一行告诉你实际使用了多少内存，
and then the next line actually tells you how much memory is actually being used
比如物理内存量，
like the amount of physical memory,
地址空间的一小部分在物理内存中，
you know, how the fraction of the address space actually is in physical memory,
正如你看到的，它通常比地址空间小得多，
and as you can see it actually it's typically way smaller than the address space
所以我们最后谈到的虚拟内存提供的技巧，很酷的想法，
and so the tricks that we talked about last word, cool ideas and virtual memory provides
在这里使用，比如按需调页，
are being used here like demand paging,
共享列是共享页面，来自共享库中，
the shared column is shared pages, you know from the shared libraries
你大体上可以看到，常驻内存比虚拟地址空间小得多。
and you see in general that basically the the resident memory is much much much smaller than the virtual address space.
也许还有几件有趣的事需要注意，
Maybe a couple other interesting things to note
看着这台机器，负载很低，
are just looking at this machine, the load is very low,
即使有 102 个用户登录。
even though they're a hundred twenty users and 102 users logged in.
你会看到有很多进程， 950 左右，
And you're gonna see there's a lot of processes, you know 950 or roughly,
注意机器已开机多长时间， 249 天，
[] note exactly how long the machine has been up, like 249 days,
你的 xv6 内核可能根本不会运行那么长时间。
your xv6 kernel is probably not up that long at all ever.
好的，这就是，关于这个有什么问题吗，
Okay, so that's you know any questions about this,
主要的一点是，大多数内存正在使用，
just sort of, you know the main point being that most memories in use
并且常驻内存通常比虚拟地址空间小得多。
and the resident memory is typically much smaller than the virtual address space.
你可以自己运行这个，如果你想看看是怎么发生的。
You're [going] to run this yourself, if you want to see you actually what's up.
有什么问题吗？
Any questions?
您可以看到 6.S081 学生中的一些人登录，
You see some of the 6.S081 students being logged in
如果你看一下，会看到很多 QEMU 在运行。
and if you look around you see a whole bunch of QEMU running.
好的，没有问题。
Okay, no questions.
让我回到今天的话题，中断。
Let me go back to the topic for today, which is interrupts.
基本的想法是很直接的，
And the basic, you know, the basic idea is really straightforward,
我们想要实现的是，
what we want to enable is that,
某种情况下，硬件需要关注。
there's going to be cases where the hardware wants attention, wants to attention now.
从网络传入数据包，
You know a packet comes in from the network
互联网网卡产生中断，
and so the network Internet network card generates an interrupt,
用户在键盘上键入一个键，键盘会产生中断。
user typed a key on the keyboard and the keyboard generates an interrupt.
软件要做什么，
And you know what the software has to do,
如果软件必须保存它的工作，
if the software has to save its work,
不管它现在在做什么，
whatever it was doing right now,
把它放在一边，进程中断，
put it on the side, you know process interrupt,
然后恢复到正在进行的工作中。
and then resume or restore, into the work that is doing.
保存和恢复与我们之前看到的机制非常相似，
And, basically that saving and restoring is very very similar to the mechanisms that we already have seen before,
即用于系统调用，还有 traps ，比如页面错误，
namely for system calls, and traps, like page fault,
它们都使用相同的机制。
they all use the same mechanism.
所以在这个意义上，中断与 traps 或系统调用没有什么不同，
So in that sense, you know interrupts are no different whatever, compared to traps or you know system calls,
但有几件事让它们有点不同，
but a couple things that make them a little bit different
以及为什么我们要花一节课来讲解它们。
and why we're actually spending a lecture on them.
所以有三个东西组成中断，
So there three basically things that make interrupts,
与系统调用和异常略有不同。
slightly different from system calls and exceptions.
第一，用一个更好的词来说，它们是异步的，
One, with a better word, I'm gonna call they're asynchronous,
我的意思是，系统调用，
and with that I mean that, the system call,
当硬件生成中断时，中断处理程序运行，
the interrupt happens when the hardware actually generate an interrupt and the interrupt handler runs,
中断处理程序可能与 CPU 上当前运行的进程无关。
the interrupt handler might actually have nothing to do with the current running process on the CPU.
所以，与进行系统调用的情况不同，
So, unlike for example where you do a system call
当系统调用发生时，你跳入内核，
or when the system call happens and then you jump into the kernel
然后我们在调用进程的上下文中运行。
then we're running in the context of the calling process.
而对于中断则不是这样，
And this is not true with interrupt,
它们可能与你正在 CPU 中运行的进程完全无关，
they might have been completely unrelated to actually a process that you know who's running in the CPU
可能与中断处理程序无关，甚至不是它调用的。
might actually have nothing to do with the interrupt handler, may not even it calls.
所以那是不同的。
So that's different.
第二，到目前为止，我们看到的并发性比以往任何时候都要多。
Second of all, there is a much more concurrency than we have seen so far,
实际上，这是讨论并发性的开始，
in fact, you know, so this is a starting place where talking about concurrency
我们将在周三的课程中详细讨论这个问题，
and we'll talk about it on Wednesday lecture a lot more,
基本的观点是，CPU 和生成的设备是并行运行的，
the basic observation is that, basically the CPU and the device that generated in, this operate in parallel,
你知道有网卡的 UART ，
you know the UART with a network card,
只是做它的事情，从网络中挑选数据包，
you know just doing its thing you know picking packets from the network,
然后在某一时刻产生中断。
and then at some point generating an interrupt.
同时，CPU 也在运行，也在做自己的事情，
And at the same time, the CPU is running and also is doing its own thing,
所以，在设备和 CPU 之间，我们有真正的并行性，
so we have true parallelism, going on between the device and the CPU
我们必须管理这种并行性，我们稍后会看到。
and we have to manage that parallelism as we'll see in a second.
最后，我将主要关注外部设备，
And finally, I'm going to focus mostly on external devices,
比如网卡和 UART ，这些必须被编程。
like network cards and UART and those have to be programmed.
每个设备都有自己的编程手册，
And basically every device has its own programming manual,
以 RISC-V 同样的方式，包含指令和寄存器作用，RISC-V有说明书和哪些寄存器做什么的手册，
in the same way that RISC-V has manual with instructions and which registers do what,
每个设备都有类似的手册，
every device actually has a similar [] manual,
描述它有什么寄存器，你可以遵循哪些操作，
with you know describing what register it has, what operations you can conform,
设备对于读取和写入控制寄存器的回应。
what the device does come in response to reading and writing control registers.
不幸的是，设备手册通常不如 RISC-V 手册清楚，
Unfortunately often the manuals for the devices are less clear than the RISC-V manual
这使得复杂的编程变得更加复杂。
and which makes a complex programming even more complicated.
我在这节课上要做的其实很简单，
And so what I'm gonna do in this lecture is actually pretty straightforward,
讨论 shell 提示符（$）是如何出现的，
if you want to talk about how the prompt shows up, when you know the shell prompt
然后如果你键入 ls ，
and then if you type ls,
这些字符是怎么读入的，
you know how do these characters get read
然后显示在控制台中，
and actually then being displayed in the console
实际上，基本上剩下的课程都是关于这三个字符的，
and in fact, so basically the rest of these lectures about these three characters,
以及实现这一目标所必需的的所有机制。
Um you know, but all the mechanism, that's necessary to actually make that happen.
到目前为止，在我继续深入讨论之前，有什么问题吗？
Any questions so far, before I [extract] diving a little deeper.
好的。
Okay.
所以可能要问的第一个问题是，中断是从哪里来的。
So the first question maybe to ask is where did the interrupts come from.
我们这节课将主要关注外部中断，
And, so so we're going to be focusing mostly this lecture on external interrupts,
不是计时器中断或软件中断，
you know not timer interrupts or software interrupts,
外部中断来自电路板上的设备，
you know the external interrupts come from devices that are sitting on the board
这是一块 SiFive 电路板，就是 QEMU 模拟的那个，
and here are a SiFive board, that QEMU more or less animates,
这里有一些小的改动，
you know there's some small modifications,
我们看到，你在这块板上看到，
and we see there's actually you look around from this board,
那里有很多不同的设备，
there's a lot of actually different devices there,
可以连接到这块板上，
can be connected to this board,
这里是以太网连接器，
here are Ethernet connector,
这是 MicroUSB，在那里，
in fact here's MicroUSB, that's over there,
这是 MicroSD 卡，
there's a MicroSD card,
这是重置按钮，
you know reset buttons
这是从这些设备到 CPU 的各种线路。
and so there are all kinds of lines that must be running running from those devices into the CPU.
这节课的大部分内容是，
And most of this lecture is basically sort of
理解当设备发生中断时， CPU 上会发生什么，
understanding, you know what happens, you know at the CPU when a device generates an interrupt
以及如何从设备读取和写入信息。
and how to read and write the information from the device.
我相信下面的两个针脚，在这个扩展接头上，
I believe like these lower two pins here, at this expansion connector,
我想其中一个是用来传输的 UART Tx ，
I think one of them is UART, is the UART sent, for transmission
另一个是用来接收的 UART0 Re 。
and the other one is the UART0 receive Re.
<---我认为它实际上与两边都有联系，
And I think it's actually connected to both sides,
the micro usb as well as to this extension cord,
我认为 UART 芯片本身，你可能在那边的芯片里。
and I think the UART chip itself, you know might actually be inside of this chip over there.
好的，所以电路板上有很多线到 CPU ，
Okay so, so basically there are a bunch of lines running on the board, you know into the CPU,
我们放大一点，详细看看 CPU ，
you know we go zoom in a little bit more in detail in the CPU,
电路板使用 SiFive 文档中的方案，
use a schema from the you know, SiFive documentation for the board
或者电路板的处理器使用 RISC-V 处理器，
or the processor of the board were RISC-V processor using,
我们之前看过这个，
we looked at this a little bit before,
看这里，右边是设备，
you know see here basically, here are the devices on the right side,
这里是 UART0 ，
here UART0
我们知道 UART0 内存映射到物理地址空间中的某个位置。
and we know that basically that UART0 memory maps somewhere in the physical address space,
这边的所有 DRAM ，
like all the DRAM on this side,
我们知道 DRAM 位于 0x8000 之上，
we know we know the DRAM sits above 0x8000
而在 0x8000 之下，是不同的设备。
and below 0x8000 they are different devices.
基本上对那些物理地址使用 load 和 store 指令，
Basically with load and store instructions, you know to those, to those physical addresses,
我们实际上可以对 UART 进行编程，
we can actually program that UART,
稍后会更详细地了解这一点。
look at that in much more detail in a second.
所有设备都可以到达处理器，
All the devices can basically coming to the processor
真正发生的是这个平台级别的中断间控制器，
and really what happens is this platform level inter- interrupt controller,
简称为 PLIC ，
which is called PLIC for short,
是对外部设备中断的管理者。
is the one that sort of general managers, the interrupts coming in, you know, from external devices.
所以如果我们再放大一点，
And so if we zoom in a little bit more,
这是片上设备 PLIC 的示意图，
here's a diagram of the the PLIC in on-chip devices,
这里看到，有 53 条中断线路来自不同的设备。
so here we see there's you know 53 interrupt lines coming in from different devices,
可能，中断线路上的设备，进入 PLIC ，
probably, devices on interrupt line, they come into the PLIC
然后 PLIC 路由这些中断。
and the PLIC and route interrupts.
举个例子，这取决于，
So, for example you know depending,
所以这是我们的核心，
so here are our particular cores,
在这里，我们运行的是三个内核，
here in our way, we run it, we run three cores
PLIC 是可以编程的，
and basically you know the PLIC can be programmed,
所以 PLIC 将中断交给这些核心中的一个或者第一个，
so that the PLIC will raise interrupts to, you know, one of these cores or to the first core,
它可以获得中断，
that can take an interrupt
而且有一些灵活性。
and there's a bit of flexibility.
如果此时没有一个核心可以接受中断，
And if none of the cores can take an interrupted at this point,
比如它们禁用了中断，
for example they have disabled interrupts,
因为他们在处理另一个中断，
because their processing another interrupt
PLIC 将持有这个中断，
and the PLIC will just hold that interrupt
直到有处理器可以处理中断。
until you know a processor is available to take interrupt.
所以 PLIC 有一些内部状态来记录这些。
So the PLIC has some internal state, you know to keep track of that.
如果你看一下文档，
If you saw the documentation a little bit,
PLIC 中真正发生的是，
in a way you know real things are happening is the PLIC,
表示有一个中断，等待其中一个核心，声称拥有它，
indicates that there is a interrupt,
pending one of the cores, you know basically claims it,
所以这告诉 PLIC 不要给任何其他核心，
so that will tell the PLIC not to give to any other core
一旦核心完全完成，
and once the core is completely done with it,
它会说好的，我完成了这个中断，
it will say OK I'm done with this particular interrupt
然后 PLIC 会，
and you know the PLIC will,
通知 PLIC 可以忘记这个中断。
inform the PLIC that [] this can forget about this interrupt.
有任何关于这个的问题吗？
Any questions about this?
这是 RISC-V 的内部中断结构。
There's sort of the internal RISC-V interrupt structure.
是的，所以当每个核心持有 PLIC 时，
Yeah, so when each core holds the PLIC,
PLIC 是否有某种执行机制来确保公平。
does the PLIC have some enforcement mechanism to ensure fairness.
这一切都取决于内核，
It is all up to the kernel
以任何它想要的方式对 PLIC 进行编程。
to program the PLIC in whatever way it wants.
PLIC 不是真的选择传送中断服务，[写入它们]，
You know PLIC doesn't really, choosing service of delivering interrupted [writing them],
但是从内核程序获取[]，将中断传递到哪里，等等。
but it takes the kernel programs [] [] where interrupts should be delivered, etc.
实际上，有优先级的中断，
In fact, you know interrupts with priorities,
内核可以决定哪个中断比另一个中断更重要，
the kernel could decide which interrupt is more important than another interrupt,
这里有很大的灵活性。
there's a huge amount of flexibility.
关于硬件的任何其他问题？
Any other questions about the hardware?
好的。
Okay.
好的，这就是它的硬件方面，
Okay, so that's the hardware side of it,
让我们从高层次上谈一下软件方面的问题。
you know let's talk a little bit you know, at a high level about the software side.
通常情况下，管理设备的代码称为驱动程序。
So, typically the code that manages devices called the driver.
你知道，基本上就是代码，
And you know basically these just just code,
通常内核查看 C 代码，
you know typically in kernels, the kernels will be looking at C code
在 xv6 中，所有的驱动程序都在内核内部，
and in xv6, you know all the drivers are inside of the kernel
这些用于管理的代码就是驱动程序，
and the code, you know basically managing were the drivers
都在内核内部。
are all inside of the kernel.
所以我们今天来看一下，
And so we got one we're gonna be looking a little bit today,
你知道 uart.c 是 UART 芯片的驱动程序。
you know uart.c is the driver for uart chip.
如果你看一下代码的内部结构，
And if you look at the structure, internal structure of the that code,
大多数驱动都有一种结构。
you know most drivers have a structure.
我来画一下，
Yeah I'm gonna draw this,
不是作为地址空间，不是使用地址空间，
not as an address space, are not intending to be using address space,
但通常情况下，当人们谈论驱动时，
but typically when people talk about drivers,
会有底部和顶部。
there's a bottom part and the top part.
一般底部是中断处理程序。
And basically the bottom part is the interrupt handler.
所以中断处理程序，当中断进入时，
So when an interrupt handler, when an interrupt comes in,
如果处理器， CPU 启用了中断，中断将会触发，
you know the processor, the CPU has interruption enabled, the interrupt will fire,
处理器随后会看到，
you know, the processor will seeing in a second,
调用该设备的中断处理程序，
will actually call the interrupt handler for that device
就是调用这里的代码。
basically calls into the code here.
并且中断处理程序运行在，任何特定进程的任意上下文中，
And the interrupt handler just runs in, run in any context of any specific process,
就是引发中断的进程。
you know just you know process, just process the interrupt.
驱动程序的顶部是，
The top part, if you will the driver is
是用户进程或者其他内核要调用的，
where user processes or you know the rest of the kernel calls into
比如 console 的例子，
for example and the console case correct
UART 有读写接口，
where UART, there's read/write interface,
是更高级别的代码调用的，
that actually, the higher level code actually calls into
通常情况下，在驱动程序中经常会有一些队列，
and so typically cases actually there's some queue often in the driver
顶部代码调用，将字符放入队列中，
and you know top level code, you know calls in, sticks you know characters into into this queue
而中断处理程序放入或，
and the interrupt handler, you know puts or,
根据发送或接收，
depending on sending or receiving,
如果是接受，
but if it's a receiving,
也许中断处理程序也会将字符放入队列中。
maybe interrupt handler else will stick actually a character's into queues.
我们会看到，使用这些队列可以使顶部和底部解耦，
We'll see you have these queues are basically used to decouple the top and the bottom part from each other
并且允许设备与 CPU 上的其他代码并行运行。
and allowing the device to run in parallel with the rest of the code on the CPU.
中断处理程序，通常对中断处理程序有一些限制，
And the interrupt handler, typically there are some restrictions on the interrupt handler,
因为它们运行在任何上下文中，
because those are run in any context,
在你可以调用 copyin 或 copyout 的进程上下文中，
you know any process context, generally you can call copyin or copyout,
因为当前页表，
because you know the current page table
可能不是对应页表，
might actually not be reflective of the page table
进程的字符应该[复制]。
that's a process to which character should be copied.
所以驱动程序的上部，通常与用户进程进行交互，
And so it's the upper part of the driver generally does the interaction with user level processes
可能调用 copyin 或 copyout 。
and maybe called copyin the copyout.
对这张高级别（示例）图片有什么问题吗？
Any questions about this high level picture?
我们会更详细地研究它，
We'll look at it in quite a bit more detail,
但这是典型驱动程序的主要组织方式，
but this is sort of the main organization of a typical driver,
如果你注意到，操作系统中有很多驱动程序，
if you're going to realize, you know there are many drivers in an operating system,
实际上，有些驱动程序代码比内核本身要大是很常见的。
in fact, it's quite common, that you know some of the driver code is quite bigger or larger than the core kernel itself.
最主要的原因是，对于每个设备，你需要一个驱动程序。
And mostly because for every device, you need to drive-, you need a driver.
而且大多数计算机都有很多设备。
And most computers have a lot of devices.
好的，让我们来谈谈对设备编程。
Okay, so let's talk a little bit about programming devices.
通常，设备编程使用内存映射 IO 。
And so typically programming is done using memory mapped IO.
正如我们在 RISC-V 或 SiFive 电路板上看到的，
So as we've seen in in RISC-V or in the SiFive board,
设备出现在物理地址空间的特定地址，
you know, devices show up at particular addresses in the physical address space,
这是由设备电路板制造商决定。
this is decided by the device board manufacturer.
操作系统需要知道，
And you know operating system needs to know,
这些设备位于物理内存空间中的哪个位置，
what those were those devices are located in the physical memory space,
然后对它们进行编程，
and then basically programs them,
对这些地址使用普通的加载存储指令。
using ordinary load and store instructions to those addresses.
这些加载存储指令所做的是，
But basically what these load store instructions do is
它们读或写设备的控制寄存器。
they they read or write, read or write control registers of the device.
所以，当你在其中一个控制寄存器中存储某些内容时，
And so typically when you store something in one of the control registers
发送你的数据包，
that causes your packet to be sent,
所以不是读或写内存，
so instead of reading, writing memory,
这些加载存储指令通常具有副作用，
these load store instructions typically have side effects,
引起设备做某些事。
the cause of the device to do something.
你必须查看设备文档，
And you know you have to look basically the documentation of the device
才能弄清楚这个设备是做什么的。
to actually figure out what the device does.
有时候文档非常清楚，
And you know sometimes this documentation is very clear,
有时候文档不太清楚。
sometimes this documentation is less clear.
这里给你一个小的示例。
This should give you a little bit of a sample, the.
在这里我想给你们看两样东西，
Two things I wanted to show you in here,
在屏幕的右侧，
on the right side of the screen,
你可以看到 SiFive 电路板的物理内存映射空间，
you see the memory map, physical memory map space, you know for the SiFive board,
你可以看到特定事物映射的地址是什么，
and you see what the addresses are where particular things are mapped,
它们出现在物理地址空间中的位置，
where they show up in the physical address space to use the [] map
它们实际出现在物理地址空间的位置。
where they actually show up in the physical address space.
比如， CLINT 在 0x0200 。
And so, for example we see the CLINT you know is there at 0x0200.
我们再挑一个。
We we pick out another one.
PLIC 也在那里的某个地方，
The PLIC was somewhere there too,
好的，这里是 PLIC ，在 0x0C00 ，
okay, here's the PLIC at 0x0C00,
这是平台中断控制器，
that's the platform platform the interrupt controller,
我们看到 UART0 在这个特定地址，
and you know we see actually UART0 here at this particular address,
实际上，在我们使用的 QEMU 上，
that turns out that on the QEMU that we're using
UART 实际上在另一个位置。
use has to UART actually at a different location.
那是因为我们使用 QEMU ，
You know, that's because we use QEMU
并不是完全模仿 SiFive 电路板，
doesn't actually literally emulate the SiFive board,
而是跟 SiFive 电路板很相似。
but something that's very close to the SiFive board.
好的，这就是内存映射，
Okay, so that's the memory map,
从物理地址到设备的内存映射。
memory map, you know physical addresses, you know to to devices.
然后，在左边，
And then, on the left side,
是 UART 文档的一部分。
is piece of documentation for UART.
这是 16550 ，
This is the 1655-, 16550,
这是位于 QEMU 上模拟的 UART 芯片，
that's actually UART chip that sits on the QEMU emulates,
我们用来与键盘和控制台交互，
that we're using to actually interact with keyboard and console
这是一个很简单的芯片，
and you know this is a reasonable simple chip,
这个设备并没有太多的功能，
there's not actually much going on in this device,
即便如此，它们还是有点复杂。
there's even then they're sort of complications.
在这张表中，
Here on the this table here,
显示了芯片拥有的寄存器，控制器寄存器，
it shows the registers that the chip has, the controller registers
比如，控制寄存器 0 0 0 ，
as for example, you know control register zero zero zero
当你执行加载指令时，
in when you're doing load instruction,
它将持有数据，
it holds, it's will hold the data,
如果执行存储指令，
if you do store instruction,
寄存器会，数据会复制进来，
that's the register, that will basically, the data will be copied into
传输到线路之外，
to be transmitted, you know, outside of the wire,
UART 是一种允许你通过串行线发送比特的设备，
UART basically a device that allows you to send bits over a serial line,
发送是一条线路，接收是另一条线路，
sent line is one line and the received line is another line,
基本上，你取一个字节
basically you take a byte
它们在这一条线上是多路复用或串行化的，
and you know basically they're multiplex or serialized on this single line
送到另一边，
sent over to the other side,
有一个 UART 芯片在另一边，
there's UART chip sitting on the other side
将比特组装回单个字节。
and basically assembles the bit back into a single byte.
你还可以在这个设备上，控制其他几件事情，
And a couple other things that you can control on this device,
你可以一定程度上控制设备的波特率，
you can actually control the baud rate of the device, to some degree,
对我们来说最重要的可能是寄存器 1 ，
and you know probably most important for us is register register one
在这里，是中断启用寄存器，
which is here which is the interrupt enable register
我们可以对它编程，
and so we can program it
使 UART 生成中断。
to actually cause UART to generate interrupts.
向下滚动，
So, in particular scroll down,
在这份文档中，你会看到。
this document you'll see that the.
向下滚动一点，
Scroll down a bit,
文档更详细地描述了每个寄存器中的每一位的含义，
the document actually more detail basically describe what every bit in every register means,
比如，在中断启用寄存器 IER 中，
in for example in the interrupt enable register IER register, which the abbr name for it,
有接收行状态中断，
you know that basically this is a receive line state interrupt
和传输保持状态中断。
and transmit holding register interrupt.
这是这些位的含义。
So that's what the bits mean.
它还有很多，有更多的文档，
It goes on and on, there's a lot more documentation
告诉你寄存器的更多细节，
and that tells you what the more detailed the registers are,
如何在轮询模式或中断模式下使用它，
how you can use it in polling mode or interrupt mode,
我们会多谈一点，
we'll talk about a little bit more,
如何对启用寄存器等进行编程，等等。
you know how, how you have to program the enable registers etc etc.
这是真实文档的一个简短版本，
So it turned out to be a short version of the real documents,
真正芯片制造商的文档要多得多，
you know the real documents where the chip manufacturers much more,
有更多的内容和更多的细节，
has much more stuff in it and much more detail
这个对我们谈论 UART 编程足够了。
and it's sufficient for us to actually be able to talk about how the program UART.
你可以看到，这是最简单的设备之一，
And you can see, this is like one of the most simple devices
即使那份文档，它也相当复杂。
and even that document you know it's quite a bit to it.
抱歉，我想知道，如果你写入，
Sorry, I was wondering, if you're writes,
如果你将某些内容写入传输保持寄存器，
so if you write something to the transmit holding register
然后你再写一遍，在那之后，
and then you write again like write after that,
它是不是确保了之前的数字不会被覆盖。
it makes sure that like the previous number didn't just like get over written, right.
是或不是，这是你来决定的，
Yes, or no, it's part of you,
实际上这是我们要关注的一件事，
actually this is one of the things that we're going to pay a bit of attention to,
你告诉，加载指令加载一些值，
the you tell, basically load instruction load some value
或存储指令将一些值加载到寄存器中，
or store instruction load some value in that register
然后， UART 芯片继续，
and then the, the UART chip goes of
它会把那个字节发送到串行线路上，
and it's going to send of that that byte onto the line, on the serial line right,
当它完成时，
and when it's done,
它将生成一个中断，告诉内核，
it will generate an interrupt saying to the kernel,
好了，完成了那个字节，
okay, I'm done with that byte,
现在你可以给我下一个字节了。
now you can give me the next byte.
因此内核和设备必须遵循一个协议，
And so the kernel and the device has to follow a protocol
以确保一切都能顺利解决。
to make sure that actually everything works out.
这个我们使用的 UART ，
This particular, UART you know that we're using
16550A 实际上内部有一个 FIFO ，
has, 16550A actually internally has a FIFO
我想它可以缓冲一些字符，
and I think it can buffer a bunch of characters,
我想最多是 16 个字符。
like I think up to sixteen.
但是你仍然要玩这个游戏，
But you still have to play this game of
你不能放入超过 16 个字符，
like you can't stick more than sixteen characters into it
在设备告诉你已经发送了一个字符之前。
until the device actually has told you well, I've sent one character.
这能理解吗？
Does that make sense?
是的，谢谢。
Okay, yeah, thank you.
我们会再多说一点，
So we'll talk a little bit more,
在看更多细节之前，
before we do look a little more detail,
我们要看的个例研究，
you know, you know the case study, you know that we going to go through
为了解释设备和中断是如何工作的，
for a sort of explaining how devices and interrupts work
是 $ ls，
is here's $ ls,
你知道这里发生了什么。
you know what happens when the.
实际上是如何打印的，
You know how actually how you print
发生的事情是，
and so basically what happens is
就像我们刚才讨论的那样，
that the device as we actually discussed in the second go,
在本例中，基本上就是把 $ 符放入 UART ，
basically puts the character of the $ in this case you know into the UART,
实际上，是我们刚看过的寄存器中。
in fact in the register that we just looked at.
然后 UART 产生中断，
And then the UART generates interrupt,
我们可以设置，
the way we can set things up,
当发送字符时产生一个中断。
generates an interrupt, when the when the character has been sent.
然后在另一边，
And then on the other side
所以 QEMU 中的事情是这样设置的，
and so basically, the way things are set up in QEMU
QEMU 在一个在发送线上，
and QEMU is on the sent line,
在发送线路的另一边，
on the other side of the sent line,
通常是另一个 UART 芯片，
it usually sits in another UART chip
它连接到控制台，
and that actually connects to the console
连接到一个虚拟控制台。
to the virtual you knows a virtual console.
另一方面，你知道 ls 会发生什么，
On the other side, you know what happens in ls,
我们需要使用输入，
is we need to use input
所以，键盘实际上连接到接收的线路，
and so the keyboard actually is connected to the receive line,
接收线。
um, receive line.
基本上就是键盘，
And, so basically the keyboard,
你按了键盘上的一个键，
you know you hit a key on the keyboard,
在本例中的虚拟键盘，
keyboard, virtual keyboard in this case,
另一边的 UART 芯片，
you know, UART chip on that side,
会序列化字符 l ，
you know will serialize you know the character l,
把它发送给另一边的 UART ，
send it to UART, on the other side,
另一边把位放在一起变成一个字节，
the other side, you know put the you know the bits, you know together again into one byte
然后产生中断，
and then generate an interrupt,
生成中断告知处理器，
generate an interrupt to tell the processor,
嘿，键盘上有一个字符可用。
hey there's a character available from the keyboard.
在中断处理程序中，收到 UART 的字节，
In the interrupt handler, the interrupt handle reach the byte from the UART
正如我们稍后看到的，
as we'll see in a second,
所以，这里有两个事情需要理解，
so those are two things that we want to understand
更详细地了解它们是如何工作的。
more detail actually how they work.
好的?
Okay?
这个有什么问题吗？
Any questions about this?
好的， RISC-V 有一系列的支持，
Okay, so, the RISC-V has a bunch of support,
对中断的支持。
support for interrupts.
我们会更详细地了解一些会使用的寄存器的细节，
And numbers of registers, you know we'll see in more detail as we could use,
但是知道有哪些是有用的，
but it's useful to know which ones there are,
这是 SIE ，管理程序中断启用寄存器，
there's the SIE, supervisor interrupt enable register
它有一位，用于外部中断，
and that has a bit, one bit for external interrupts,
来自设备，比如 UART ，
from devices, like the UART,
来自软件中断，这一点我会讨论一下，
from software interrupts, which I'm really going to talk about it,
但这是可能的，从一个 RISC-V 核心
but it is possible from one CPU from one RISC-V cores
向另一个 RISC-V 核心发送中断，
to send an interrupt to another RISC-V core,
还有定时器中断。
and timer interrupt.
我不准备谈论管理者模式的软件中断或计时器中断，
And I'm not really going to talk about either you know the supervisor of the software interruption or the timer interrupts,
而是重点放在外部中断。
are going to focus on external interrupts.
还有另一个我们见过的寄存器，
There's another register that we've seen before,
管理者状态寄存器，
the supervisor status register,
它有一个位用来禁用和启用特定内核上的中断。
and that has a bit to disable and enable interrupts on this particular core.
所以，每个核心都有这些寄存器，
So every core has you know these registers
除了这三个位之外，
and there's, in addition to these three bits,
对于每个控制，你有外部中断、软件中断、计时器中断，
for individual control, when you want to have external interrupts, software interrupt, timer interrupt,
有一个位可以控制收到的中断，
there's one bit that controls you're going to receive interrupts at all,
所以，你可以原子地从没有中断切换到可以中断，
so you can atomicly switch from not getting interrupts to having interrupted,
反之亦然，
the other way around,
只需要修改 SSTATUS 寄存器中的这一位。
just changing that one bit in the SSTATUS register.
然后是 SIP 寄存器，
And then there's a SIP register
称为管理程序中断挂起寄存器，
are the called the supervisor interrupt pending register,
基本上进程可以使用它，
and basically the process you can use that
当中断发生，
you know want to interrupt it happened,
查看 SIP ，看是什么中断。
look at the SIP to see what, what interrupt actually has come in.
另外，当中断发生时，
And in addition, there will be even interrupt happens,
在 SCAUSE 寄存器，我们之前已经看过几次，
in the SCAUSE register, we should that we have seen a couple times before now,
将会出现一个进入的中断的指示，我们随后会看到，
there will be an indication of one interrupt actually came in, we'll look in the second
当然还有 STVEC 寄存器，
and of course there's the STVEC register,
保存程序，或处理器切换的地址，
basically holds the program or address to which the processors switch
当 trap 系统调用，
once either trap or trap system call
或发生页面错误，产生中断，
or page fault happens when an interrupt happens,
因为这三种情况都使用相同的机制。
because basically uses for all three cases the same mechanism.
我不会说太多关于 SCAUSE 和 STVEC ，
I'm not gonna talk too much about SCAUSE and STVEC,
因为我们之前已经详细看过了，
because we've seen it in detail before,
基本上以相同的方式运行，
and basically operates exactly in the same way
与页面错误或其他异常的系统调用一样。
as as system calls in page faults or other exceptions.
好的，让我们来看看，
Okay, so let's see a little bit of sense,
这些东西是如何初始化的，
how this stuff is sort of initialized,
我们不会谈论驱动的实际工作方式，
so we're not talking even about how the drivers actually work,
而是看看 xv6 程序是如何对它编程，
but just see how xv6 programs this,
设置这些寄存器，让我们处于中断的位置。
these registers set we're going to be in a position to take a interrupt.
聊天中有一个问题，确认一下。
These's a question from the chat, make sure that.
好的，
Alright, okay.
聊天有点落后，
A little behind on the chat,
那么让我们来看一下， xv6 如何对寄存器编程，
so let's see a little bit on the what, xv6 programs registers,
所以找出一些代码。
so pull up some code.
让我跳出这个这个窗口，
Let me get rid of the this window,
其实我也不需要这个。
actually I don't really need that either.
我不打算使用 gdb 来遍历代码，
I'm not going to run use gdb to walk through things,
我只想看看相关的特定函数。
I'm just going to look at you know particular functions that are relevant.
所以，第一件事可能是在 start.c 中，
So probably the first thing is in start.c.
当机器启动时，处理器启动时，
So when the machine boots, what processor boots,
start 函数被调用，
the the start function is called,
它以 M 模式运行，
its runs in the M mode,
它禁用了页表，
and it disables paging,
因为很快，稍后，
so right away, because you know sort of later on,
内核可以设置页表，
the kernel can set up the page tables
我们在这里看到，
and we see here that
将所有中断和异常交给管理者模式，
basically delegates all interrupts and exceptions to supervisor mode,
然后，对管理者中断启用寄存器编程，
then it's programs the supervisor enable interrupt enable register
用来接受软件中断，定时器中断，以及外部中断。
to take software interrupts, timer interrupts, and external interrupts.
然后为了更好的[衡量]，
And then for good [measure],
定时器中断发生在 M 模式，
timer interrupts actually happened to coming to are handled in M mode,
M 模式代码对定时器寄存器编程，
the M mode code, actually programs, the timer registers
然后产生计时器中断。
and so that timer timer interrupts are generated.
我不想讨论这个，
I don't want to talk about that actually,
所以，我要去看 main.c 。
so I'm gonna go to main.c.
看看外部设备是如何处理的，
And so see how external devices are handled
我们的第一个外部设备是可以打印的 console 。
and so our first external devices is the console where we print to.
我们可以看看 consoleinit 做了什么。
And we can see what consoleinit does.
这是 consoleinit ，
So here's consoleinit,
初始化锁，实际上我们不关心这个，
initialize lock, we actually care not much about that at all,
它不是这节课（的内容），
it's not for this lecture,
它调用了 uartinit 。
and it actually basically calls that uartinit.
uartinit 在这里。
And uartinit is right here.
它设置了 UART 芯片，
It actually sets up the uart chip,
配置要使用的 UART 芯片。
configure uart chips that is ready for use.
首先是禁用中断，
You know first actually disables interrupts,
你知道有一个顺序，
you know there's the sequence,
当你对它编程时，必须遵守，
you have to go through when you program it,
然后，你可以设置波特率，
then you can set the baud rate,
然后设置 6 7 位，
then you set in six you know seven bits,
7 位或 8 位[修复] UART 。
you know seven or eight bit bits will [repaired] uart.
然后，重新设置 UART 的内部 FIFO ，
And, you reset the internal FIFO that's uart has
清除那里可能存在的任何东西，
to clear out anything that actually might be in there
然后，接收到，
and then, will receive,
它将启用传输中断和接收中断。
it will enable interrupts for transmission and receive interruption.
Amir ，我想你举手了。
Amir, I think you raise your hand.
是的，我想知道波特率是什么。
Yeah, I'm wondering what the baud rate is exactly.
哦，是线路运行的速度。
Oh the speed which you know the lines runs.
我知道了，谢谢。
I see, thanks.
好的，那就是 uartinit 。
Okay, so that's uartinit.
现在，原则上 UART 可以生成中断，
Now at this point you know the uart in principle can generate interrupts,
但是当然我们还没有对中断启用寄存器编程，
but of course we are we haven't actually programm the interrupt enabling stuff
在 RISC-V 处理器上，
on the on the RISC-V processor itself,
我们还没有对 PLIC 编程，
we haven't programmed to PLIC yet,
这个时候，什么都不会发生。
nothing really happens at this point yet.
所以下一件事，我们将回到 main.c ，
And so the next thing, we're going to move back to main.c,
我们会看到，向下滚动一点，
you know we'll see, a little bit scroll down,
我们会看到 PLIC 初始化，
we'll see actually that the PLIC is initialized,
让我们来看看这个。
so let's look at that.
基本上， plicinit 代码，
And basically, you know, plicinit code,
如果看一下我刚才给你的这张表格，
if you look at this table that I showed you a little while ago,
物理内存或内存布局，
with the physical memory or the memory layout,
你知道， PLIC 在某个特定的位置，
you know the PLIC is in some particular location right,
位置在 kernel/memlayout.h 。
location is in kernel/memlayout.h.
我们看到 PLIC 是 0C000000 ，
We see the PLIC 0C000000 correct,
字面上是从那份文档复制过来的。
literally copied from that document.
我们向 PLIC 写东西，
And you know the way we write stuff to the PLIC
使用 PLIC 的地址编号，
is basically you take the number the address for the PLIC
强制转换为 32 整数指针，
cast to a 32 pointer integer,
因为 PLIC 寄存器是 32 位的。
because the PLIC registers are 32 bit.
然后写入，
And then basically write onto it,
这个强制转换是将 1 写入寄存器 UART0_IRQ 。
so this cast is basically one to be written to the register UART0_IRQ.
这个说做的就是，
And basically what this does is
它启用来自 UART 的中断请求，
it enables interrupt requests from the uart,
记得 PLIC 路由中断，
so remember the PLIC basically routes interrupts,
所以中断可能从图片左侧进入 PLIC ，
and so the interrupt might come in from the left side from that picture into the PLIC
这个程序中， PLIC 可以接受这些中断。
and the PLIC, like this program PLIC to actually accept those interrupts.
类似地，对 PLIC 编程，从 IO 磁盘接收中断，
Similarly, actually programs the PLIC to accepting interrupts from the IO disk,
我不会讨论论这个。
which I'm not going to talk about at all.
好的，然后，我们回到 main.c 。
Okay, and then, we go back, you know to main.c.
在 plicinit 之后，是 plicinithart ，
And there right after the plicinit is just plicinithart
针对每个核心，每个独立核心，
and then basically for every cores specifically, every core individually,
只有一个核心，第一个核心初始化该方面，
so only one core, the first core actually initialize this [aspect],
我们接收这些设备的中断，
basically we're taking interrupts on those devices
然后，每个核心都必须单独地说我也对这些设备感兴趣。
and then every core individually has to say I'm interested in those devices too.
比如，在这里，
And so for example here,
每个核心都调用这些函数，
every core actually calls these functions,
每个核心，都对来自 UART 的中断感兴趣，
every cores, interested in interrupt from uart
也对 VIRTIO 的中断感兴趣。
and I'm interested the interrupts from the virtio.
你在这里可以看到 UART0_IRQ ，
You can see here basically the UART0_IRQ,
是一个唯一的数字，
basically is a unique number,
UART_IRQ 在 UART 中，
you know for, the UART_IRQ for in what uart,
我想在 QEMU 上是编号 10 。
and I think believes on the on QEMU number ten.
我们忽略 priority ，
And we're basically ignore priority
所以我们把它设为零。
and so we just set it to zero.
好的，每个 CPU 单独调用，
Okay, and so does every CPU already called individually
必须向 PLIC 表明，
has to indicate to the PLIC,
它对接收中断感兴趣。
that actually is interested in receiving interrupts.
在这一点，你知道 PLIC ，
You know, at this point you know we're you know the PLIC basically,
所以我们必须对设备进行编程以产生中断，
so we basically have to program the device to generate interrupts,
我们对 PLIC 编程在各个 CPU 上传递中断，
we have program to PLIC you know to pass interrupts on the individual CPUs,
但是 CPU 本身还没有接受中断，
but the CPU itself have actually are not accepting interrupt yet,
因为我们还没有设置 SSTATUS 寄存器中的位，
because we haven't set the bit in the SSTATUS register yet
所以，让我们回到 main.c 。
and so let's go back to to main.c.
main.c 做了更多初始化，
And whatever main.c does a bunch of more initialization,
但是，最后它调用了 scheduler 。
but in the end it actually calls the scheduler.
所以，我们来看一下 proc.c ，
So let's look at proc.c,
搜索 scheduler 。
and get scheduler.
我们在这里看到的是，
And what we see here,
整个机器的，
is like when the around basically the whole machine
处理器已经设置，
is sort of the processors has been setup
调度器调度虚拟进程运行，
and scheduler schedules virtual process run,
在任何一个启用中断之前。
before you know any of that actually enables interrupts.
所以，我们来看看 riscv.h 。
And so we look at riscv.h.
你们会看到，这是一个 C 函数。
You'll see, there's basically this is a C function.
它启用中断
And basically enables interrupts
你不会感到惊讶，
and you can not surprising
它唯一能做的就是，
you know basically the only thing it does,
设置 SSTATUS 寄存器中的中断启用位。
it sets the interrupt enable bit in the sstatus register.
在这个特殊的时刻，
So at this particular point time,
如果在 PLIC 处存在挂起的中断，
right at this instance if there were an interrupt pending at the PLIC,
那么这个特殊的核心会被中断。
then you know the this particular core would be interrupted.
我们随后会看到，
We see that a second later,
但是，此时启用了中断。
but this is this point interrupts are enabled.
这就是基本设置。
And so this is the basic setup.
对于这个，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about this?
不好意思，
Oh, sorry,
在那个时刻，哪个核心会被打断呢？
oh, what core would be interrupted when at that point?
所以，每个核心都运行调度器循环。
So every core runs the scheller loop, correct.
无论什么核心启用中断，
And whatever core calls interrupt on,
所有内核都会启用中断，
all cores will call interrupt on,
但是我们假设只有一个核心最先到达那里，比如核心 1 ，
but let's say there's only one core gets there first, like core one
如果核心 1 在这个时刻设置中断启用位，
and if core one sets its interrupt enable bit at that point,
它可能会收到中断。
it could receive an interrupt.
我们随后会看到，一次中断到底发生了什么。
And we'll see in second what happens exactly in an interrupt.
理解了，谢谢。
Makes sense, thank you.
好的，那么我想做的是，
Okay, okay, so what do I want to do
就是看看这个，
is look at this,
如何打印 $ ，
how, how to print the $
也就是 shell 提示符。
you know the prompt at the shell prompt.
所以，我们往回一点。
And so for that we want to go back a little bit.
我们首先再次查看 init 。
And our first want to look at init again.
所以，这是第一个出现的进程，
So this was the first process that actually being,
在 execinit 代码中，
there in the code execinit,
这是第一个运行的进程。
and so that's basically first process running.
它所做的一件事是，
And one of the things that it does,
它建立了一个代表控制台的设备。
it makes a device that represents the console.
这是创建的设备，
So here the device created,
使用 mknod 操作，
using the mknod operation
并且返回文件描述符，文件描述符零，
and returns a file descriptor, a file descriptor zero,
因为它是第一个打开的文件描述符，
because it's the first file descriptor open
然后分配给标准输出，
and then adopt it for stdout,
然后再分配给标准错误，
and then for stderr and adopt it again
所以，这设置了文件描述符 0 、 1 和 2 ，
and so this basically sets up file descriptor zero one and two
对应于 console 。
to correspond to the console.
现在，对于 shell 。
Now, so you know then for the shell.
让我们来看一下 shell 。
So let's look at shell for a second.
shell 打开使用文件描述符 1 2 3 ，
So the shell opens you know starts running with the file descriptors one two three,
不好意思， 0 1 2 open 只想 console ，
sorry zero one and two open pointed to the console
然后 shell 将打印 $ 和空格到文件描述符 2 。
and then shell prints the character $ and the space to file descriptor two.
因此，尽管 console 和 UART ，
And so, so even though the console and uart,
这些都属于应用程序员，
you know sort of all you know [] this to the application programmer,
比如 shell ，当然，我们需要 shell ，
and like the shell, of course, we want the shell,
它看起来就像一个普通文件，
it just looks like a regular file,
所以实际上， shell 本身，
so in fact the shell itself,
它写入文件描述符 2 ，
since its writes to descriptor two
实际上并不知道另一边是什么，
has no idea what actually sits on the other side
我们已经在 util 实验中看到，
and we have seen in util lab,
你可以用它做各种很酷的事情。
you can do all kinds of cool stuff with it.
这里有一个例子，
But here's an example
Unix 中的设备表示为一个文件，
where basically the device in Unix is represented as a file,
这和其他东西没什么不同。
that's not different than anything else.
好的，让我们看看这个 printf 是如何工作的。
Okay, so let's see how this actually printf works.
所以， xv6 用户应用程序中有一个 printf ，
So there's a printf is in xv6 user application,
一个很小的 C 库，包括 printf 代码。
a tiny little C library, which includes code printf.
printf ，像你在 traps 实验中看到的，
And you know printf, you know as you've seen in the traps lab,
是某种[本能]函数，
you know, sort of an instinct function itself,
但是，最终它调用了 write 系统调用，
but in the end it basically calls the write system call,
在我们的示例中， write 系统调用是文件描述符 2 ，
and in our case where the write system call would be you know file descriptor two
而 c 包含 $ 符号，
and c would be hold the character $
因此我们传递包含 $ 的内存地址
and so we pass the address of the memory location that holds the $
给文件描述符用来写入，
to the file descriptor to write
我们要求写入一个字符。
and we ask you know to write one character.
所以 shell 写入的每个字符，
So basically every character written by the shell,
它会引起系统调用。
it results in a system call.
现在我们可以去。
And so now we can go.
让我们看看实际会发生什么。
Let's see what actually happens.
你之前看见过系统调用，
So we you know you've seen the system call before,
但是， sysfile.h 。
but sysfile.
sys_write 。
sys_write.
这是 write 系统调用和它的参数，
So here's the write system call, [] its arguments,
文件描述符，要写入的字节数，
file descriptor, number bytes to be written
还有地址，
and the address with the,
包含 $ 的地址，
the address that it contains you know the character $,
调用 filewrite 。
call them filewrite.
让我们快速看一下 filewrite 。
Let's quickly look at filewrite.
好的，我们离我们想要讨论的东西越来越近了。
Okay, we're getting close to actually things that we want to talk about.
在这里， filewrite 查看文件描述符类型，
And you know here is filewrite it looks for the type of the file descriptor is,
如果是管道，调用管道的函数，
it's a pipe called the pipe functions,
如果是设备，不起作用，
and if its device which you know [make not does],
然后，它对那个设备调用 write 函数。
then it will call the write function for that particular device.
所以，这实际上会调用 console 中的 write 函数。
And so we know that you know that actually is going to call the write function in the console.
让我们看看那里会发生什么。
And so let's see what happens there.
这里是 consolewrite ，
So here's consolewrite,
获取锁，我们现在不关心这个，
grab lock, we don't care about that right now,
它使用 either_copyin 复制进一个字符，
it copies in the one character use either_copyin,
然后，调用 uartputc 。
and then, calls uartputc.
它调用进入 UART ，
So that basically calls into the uart,
你可以这样考虑，
and so you can think about to it,
console 是驱动程序，
the console is being the driver,
我们现在看的是驱动程序的顶端，
we're looking at the top end of the driver
现在调用 uart.c 中的东西，
and now make some call in uart.c
来打印一个字符。
to actually a print a character.
这是 uart.c ，这会有点有趣，
And so here uart.c, so this is going to be a little bit interesting,
基本上，UART 内部保持一个缓冲区，
basically the internally the uart keeps a buffer,
让我们回退一点。
so let's go back back up a little bit.
在顶部，有一个用于传输的缓冲区，
At the top, in fact there's a buffer for transmission
缓冲区大小是 32 个字符。
and buffer size is 32 characters.
这里有一个指针，写指针和读指针，
And there's a pointer the write pointer and the read pointer
用来将该字符放入循环缓冲区中，
that being used to put this character into a circular buffer,
更详细地讨论一下这个，
talk a little bit about that in more detail,
但是，有一个指向生产者的指针和一个指向消费者的指针。
but there's a pointer for the producer and as a pointer for the consumer.
在这种情况下， shell 是生产者，
And in this case, you know the shell, if you will, as the producer
它检查，
and it actually checks,
它做的第一件事是
the first thing it does is
检查这个循环缓冲区是否已满。
actually check whether this circular buffer is full.
检查循环缓冲区是否已满的方法，
So and the way the checks with the circular buffer is full,
它的初始状态是写指针和读指针都是零，
so it starts out in the original state is both the write pointer and the read pointer is zero, correct,
缓冲区的零索引，
zero index into the buffer,
如果它们相等，则缓冲器是空的，
if the equal you know that there buffer is empty,
但是如果在写指针上加一，
but if you add one to the write pointer,
与接收指针相同，
it's the same as the receive pointer,
比如，如果你填入 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 到 31 ，
so for example if you you fill in a zero one two three four five six seven eight nine to thirty one
然后你要绕回来，
and then you're about to wrap around,
加上一，它仍然等于接收索引或读索引，
you know add one if then and it's still equal to the receive index or the read index
你知道缓冲区已满。
that you know that the buffer is full.
所以，这一点上你不能写任何东西，
And so there's no point you know you can't write anything at that point,
因为很明显 UART 正忙，
because apparently UART still busy,
以它的方式工作，
you know working its way through,
试着发送之前的 31 个或 30 个字符。
trying to send off the [] you know 31 characters or 30 characters.
在这种缓冲已满的情况下，
In this case, the buffer full,
shell 会休眠，在旁边等待，
the shell basically were put to sleep and put on the side
内核将运行其他程序，
and the kernel will run some other program
直到 shell 唤醒，已经准备好发送，
until shell woken up and it's actually ready to send,
或者 UART 准备好发送更多数据。
or the uart just ready to send more data.
当然这种情况下不是这样的，
You know, of course in this case it's not the case right,
因为有几个字符正在打印，
because there's the first few characters that are being printed,
所以缓冲里有空间，
so there's space in the buffer
所以驱动程序将一个字符放入缓冲区，
and so basically the driver puts character into the buffer,
更新写指针到下一个插槽，
updates the write pointer to go to the next slot
然后调用 uartstart 。
and then calls uartstart.
基本上 uartstart 不做别的事，
And basically uartstart is nothing else,
通知设备，去帮我做点事吧。
sort of kicking the device and saying like hey go do some work for me.
还有，嗯。
And, um.
基本上，首先检查设备是否正忙，
And basically, first checks if the device is still busy,
发送当前字符，
sending the current character [] recently,
如果设备正忙，
if if the device is busy,
我们只要回去，可能会睡眠，
you know we just go back and we'll go to sleep probably,
我们会睡眠，
we'll go to sleep
否则我们从缓冲区读取字符，
and otherwise we'll read the character out the buffer
并将其放入传输寄存器中，
and put it in the transmission register,
就像我们之前看到的。
that we saw earlier.
所以传输寄存器就像之前这样，
And so the transmission register just like this before,
稍后我们看一下。
let's look at that for a second.
WriteReg 把指定的寄存器转换成 Reg 类型，
You know WriteReg you know cast the particular register to the one of Reg type,
然后，将值写入其中。
and then writes the value into it.
传输保持寄存器 THR 是
And you know THR the transmitter holding register is
我们之前在文档中看到的寄存器 0 。
register zero which we saw before from the documentation.
好的，所以，你知道，
Okay, so, so basically you know the,
我从哪里开始。
where am I start.
你应该首先从通知设备，
You should start basically kicks the device
然后说，我有一个寄存器，
and saying like hey I gotta register,
我有一个字节可以发送。
I got a byte for you available to send off.
这就是所有的。
And that's basically all the.
这就是， shell ，
And that basically the if you will, the shell,
系统调用 shell 所做的，
you know the system call, the shell call will do
如果通知设备，会回到用户空间，
and once actually kick the devices will return to user space
shell 可以继续运行，做它想做的任何事情，
and the shell can go on and do whatever it wants to do
shell 要做的下一件事就是调用 read 系统调用，
and presumably the next thing the shell will do is called the read system call
真正读取来自键盘的输入。
to actually read input from the keyboard.
所以 shell 将返回用户空间，
So the shell will return to user space,
使用我们看过的机制，比如 userret ，
using the standard mechanism, that we have seen before, like userret,
它继续，并做着自己的事，
it just goes off and does its thing
同时，那个设备没有被通知，
and in the meantime, the device has not got any kick
来真正发送一些字节。
to actually, send some bytes off.
所以。
And so.
所以，在某个时候我们会被中断，
So, at some point we're going to get interrupted,
希望，因为我们进入产生中断的硬件，
hopefully you know because we broke into the hardware to actually generate interrupts,
我们往回一点，
let's go a little bit back
讨论一下，当中断发生时发生了什么。
and talk a little bit about what happens when the interrupt happens.
好的，那么硬件做了什么。
Okay, so, so what does the hardware do.
在这种情况下， RISC-V 实际发生中断，
In this particular case, the RISC-V, do what interrupt actually happens,
所以，我们设置 SSTATUS 寄存器中的中断启用位，
so we set this interrupt enable bit in the SSTATUS register,
所以，这个进程可以被中断，
so the process can be interrupted,
比如，键盘发起中断到 PLIC ，
let's say the keyboard raises the interrupt line goes through the PLIC,
PLIC 将中断路由到特定的内核，
PLIC routes the interrupt to particular core
那个核心设置了 SIE 位，
and that core you know, has the SIE bit set,
所以，设置中断启用位，
so interrupt enable bit set,
设置管理者中断启用位，
the supervisor interrupt enable bit set,
所以，如果设置了该位，
so if the bit is set,
会发生以下情况。
the following things happen.
这个跟我们之前看到的很像，
And this will look very similar to what we've seen before,
硬件要做的第一件事就是清除 SIE 位。
but the first thing the hardware does is clear the SIE bit.
这会阻止任何进来的中断，
This stops you know any further interrupts coming in,
这样我们就可以先处理这些中断，
so that we can just deal with these interrupt first
如果我们想要更多的中断，
and then if we want more interrupts,
我们必须重新启用那个位，
you know we have to re-enable that bit,
你知道这些阻止更多的中断，
you know these to stops further interrupts
中断，中断，中断，
were basically interrupt interrupt interrupt,
然后，设置异常程序计数器 SEPC 为当前 PC 。
then it sets the SEPC to the exception program counter to the current PC.
比如，如果中断，
For example, if we were interrupted,
比如 shell 返回用户空间，
let's say the shell return to user space
在用户空间运行时发生中断，
what's happening run in user space and interrupt comes in,
因为发送了一个字符，
because of that one character is sent,
然后，程序计数器收到，在用户空间中的程序计数器，
then the program counter can receive is whatever program counter was in user space,
它保存当前模式。
it saves the save the current mode.
比如，在这种情况下，
So in this case would be an example would be
我们将保存 xv6 的用户模式，
we would save that xv6 supervisor mode, the user mode,
然后，它设置为管理者模式。
then it's sets the mode supervisor.
将程序计数器设置为 stvec 的值，
And, basically sets the program counter to stvec,
不管 stvec 的值是什么，
whatever value is in stvec, right,
然后，继续 usertrap ，或 uservec ，或 kernelvec ，
then it's going to be either usertrap or uservec or kernelvec,
取决于中断发生在什么地方，
depending whether the interrupt happens,
我们是在内核空间还是在用户模式，
you know whether we're in [] kernel space or user mode,
在我们的例子中，shell 可能会返回用户空间。
but in our example, where maybe shell return to user space,
stvec 会包含用户[]地址，
you know stvec will contain the user [] address
核心将恢复内核，
and basically the hart will resume the kernel,
到位于 stvec 中的指令，
at the instruction that is located stvec
我们还记得上一节课，
and you know we remember from previous lecture,
stvec 继续并调用 usertrap 。
you know basically stvec goes off and calls usertrap.
好的，最后我们会在 usertrap 中。
Okay, so in the end, we'll basically end up in usertrap.
这就是我们讲的故事，
And that's where we sort of pick up the [story],
我不想谈论太多关于保存和恢复的事情，
because like I don't really want to talk too much about the saving and restoring anymore,
因为，第一我们在之前的课中详细解释过，
because one we explained it in detail in the previous lecture,
第二，你已经看见过，在之前的的 traps 实验中，
two, you already played with and also in this last traps [] lab,
所以，你很清楚发生了什么。
so you know you know exactly what's going on.
有什么问题呢？
And questions?
好的，那么。
Okay, so.
所以，这里我们回到 usertrap ，
So here we back in usertrap,
它是你在 traps 实验里详细研究过的函数。
you know function you've looked in detail at in the traps lab.
我们处理了一个系统调用的案例。
And you know we dealt with a case of system calls.
我们要做的，我们要做的一件事是，
And what we're gonna do, is basically the only thing we're gonna do is
看看这个例子，设备中断。
look at this case, which is the device interrupt.
好的，所以我们要。
Okay, so so we're gonna.
这在文件的稍低一点的地方。
That's a little bit lower here in the file.
这是设备的中断，
So here's the device's interrupt
它查看 scause 寄存器，
and it looks basically the scause register
查看这是否是外部中断，
and sees if this is an external interrupt,
如果是外部中断，
and if it's an external interrupt,
它调用函数 plic_claim ，
that calls a function the plic_claim,
声称那个特定的中断。
to basically claim that particular claim interrupt.
让我们回到 plic ，
So let's go back to plic,
查看 plic_claim ，
and look at the plic_claim
归结起来就是，这个，
and basically what it boils down to is that the, in the,
特定的 CPU 会告诉 PLIC ，
this particular CPU will tell the plic,
嘿，我在请求说 CPU 0 或 CPU 1 ，
hey I'm claiming you know it's CPU zero or CPU one,
它会告诉 PLIC CPU 1 正在请求这个特定的中断，
it will tell the plic that CPU one is claiming this particular interrupt
一旦收到中断请求， PLIC 返回它得到的中断，
and once claim interrupt and plic returns which interrupts it gets,
实际传入的中断的 irq ，
irq for the interrupt that actually came in
在这种情况下，这是一个中断 UART0_IRQ 10 。
and so in this case that will be an interrupt UART0_IRQ ten.
所以 plic_claim 会返回 10 。
So plic_claim will basically return ten.
然后在这段代码中，
And then here in this code,
嘿，这是中断 10 ，
you know look you say hey is this a interrupt ten,
如果是中断 10 一定是 UART 中断，
if interrupt ten that must be a uart interrupt
然后我们调用 uartintr 函数。
and we basically called uartintr function.
而 uartintr 函数，
And uartintr function,
从 UART 把字符拿出来，
runs and basically gets the character off you know the uart
它从 uart 获取字符的方式是，
and the way it gets the character of uart is
在第一个寄存器中查找，接收寄存器，
basically looks in first register, the receive register
从那里拿出字符。
and gets the character out of there.
这是一个整数，然后它调用 consoleintr ，
And, that is an integer and then it calls consoleintr,
来做剩下的工作。
to do the rest of the work.
好的?
Okay?
不好意思，我说错了，
Actually sorry, I just did the wrong thing,
我们在谈论传输。
we were talking about transmission.
所以，如果在读取端有一个字符，
So if there was a character on the read side
然后我们会调用 consoleintr ，
and then we'll call consoleintr,
但是在读取端没有字符，
but there is no character correct, on the read side,
因为我们没有读取，键盘还没有做任何事情，
because we haven't read any, keyboard hasn't done anything yet,
我们只是在传输一个字符，
we're just transmitting a character,
那么这个会返回 -1 ，
so this like return minus one fall through
然后唯一能做的就是，
and then basically the only thing that will do
将调用 uartstart ，
is called it will call uartstart
发送在缓冲器中的任何其他字符，
to basically send any any other characters that might be in the buffer,
可能是 shell 放在这里的，
the shell, it might be stuck in there
有另一个字符的时候恢复，
and resume there's another character in there,
因为 $ 之后是空格，
because after the $ is the space
并且 write 系统调用可能，
and the write system call might,
写空格可能跟设备发送同时发生，
write this space might have happened concurrently while the device was sending off
所以，当传输中断完成时，
and so when we interrupt transmit interrupt complete,
它继续在缓冲器中找另一个字符，
it's goes off you know the, will find in the buffer yet another character,
空格字符，然后把空格字符送出。
the space character and will send space character off.
好的，这能理解吗？
Okay, that makes sense?
我有一个高层次的问题。
I have a high level of question actually.
我知道 UART 很有用，
So I understand the uart [] is like useful,
比如使用键盘，
if like using the keyboard
键盘上的字符通过 UART ，
and like characters from the keyboard go through the uart
然后通过 CPU ，
and then through the CPU
然后是我们编写的内核代码，
and then the kernel code that we wrote,
但是我不理解的是，
but I am not sure I understand what
当 UART 打印字符时，
the point of the uart is when the shell is printing characters,
比如没有键盘交互。
like the keyboard isn't being interacted with.
这是正确的，
You know, it is correct,
但是显示器是，
but the display is,
实际上有两个设备，
actually there's two devices here,
一个是键盘，一个是 console 上的显示器。
one is the keyboard and one is the display on the console.
QEMU 与 console 交互是通过 UART ，
And the way you know QEMU interact with the console is by uart,
通过发送字符到控制台，
by sending a character to the console
然后 console 的工作是
and then the console's job is
在显示器上绘制该字符。
basically to draw that character on the display.
哦，我明白了，好的，谢谢。
Oh I see, okay, thanks.
这可能需要时间，
It might take time
它需要画出这些东西。
and that's why you know this thing you know sort of being drawing.
好的。
Okay, um.
所以现在有几件事，
So a couple things now,
我想退回去一点，
you know I want to step back a little bit
从更高层次上考虑这件事，
and think a little bit higher level what's going on,
所以我们应该遍历代码，
so we should walk through the code,
我们对这里的情况有一些理解，
we get sort of a feeling for the lay of the land,
比如细节怎样，
and like how the details,
它值得退回一点，
it's worthwhile to step back a second
想一想这一切意味着什么。
and think a little bit about you know what it all means.
特别是，有趣的是并发中断，
In particular, what is interesting is interrupting concurrency,
从并发的角度考虑中断。
sort of think about interrupting the perspective concurrency.
这是使中断变得棘手或难以编程的一件事，
And this is one of the things actually makes interrupts tricky or difficult to program,
首先是我们之前提到过，
so first of all, you know we mentioned earlier,
在我们的例子中的 UART 设备，
the device you know uart in our case,
设备和 CPU 并行运行。
the device and the CPU run in parallel.
所以，比如，在我们讨论的场景中，
So, one example is in our you know scenario, what you know talk about,
UART 发送一个字符给 console ，
you know uart sending off you know a character to the console,
在这个发生的同时， CPU 仍在继续它的工作，
and while that's happening, the CPU still you know go about its business
在这种情况下，返回到 shell ，
and in this case, returning to the shell,
shell 可以调用其他的系统调用写入空格字符，
the shell may make another system call attempt to write space character
所有这些都是并行进行的，
and all happens in parallel
所以我们需要管理这种并行性，
and so we need to manage that parallelism a bit
我们已经看过一点，
and we already saw a little bit,
但我会更详细地讨论一下。
but I'm gonna talk a little bit more in detail.
这里显示的并行性，
And the type of parallelism that actually shows up here
通常称为生产者-消费者并行性。
is typically called producer consumer parallelism.
我稍后讲一下，
Let me talk about in a second,
所以现在我们更详细地讨论一下。
so now we're gonna talk about it a little more detail.
第二个是，
The second is,
中断停止了当前正在运行的程序，
that the interrupt stops the current running program,
或者正在运行的当前程序。
or the current program is running.
所以在 shell 的情况下，
So in the case of the shell,
shell 程序可能正在执行类似 212 的指令，
shell might be executing instruction like 212
然后突然出现了中断，
and boom interrupt comes in
直接在这一点停下来。
and immediate that point is just stopped.
对用户空间的代码来说，这没什么大不了的，
And that's something, you know for user space code, that's not a particularly big deal,
因为当我们从中断返回，
because when we return from the interrupt,
我们会恢复用户级别程序的所有状态，
when we restore all the state of the user level program
它会恢复出现中断的地址，
and it will resume you know at you know address which got interrupted
我们已经在 traps 和页面错误中看到了，
and so we've seen that with traps and page faults,
实际上是相当不错的，
and so you know, actually works out reasonable well,
不过，这里有个棘手的情况，
but there's a little bit of tricky case,
当内核本身中断时，
when the kernel itself interrupted,
所以如果是在内核模式下运行，
so you're running in kernel mode
而且内核被中断，
and the kernel gets interrupted,
这意味着，再说得更详细一点，
that means that, and talk a little bit more detail,
即使是内核也不是直接按顺序执行的，
that even the kernel doesn't really sort of executed straight sequentially,
如果你看到一条内核指令后跟另一条内核指令，
if you see one kernel instruction followed by another kernel instruction,
在这些指令之间，中断可能发生，
in the between those instructions and interrupt might happen,
取决于是否启用中断。
depending whether interrupts are enabled or not.
在一些代码中，
In so whether, and some piece of code
在中间可以中断是不好的，
and it's not good to have an interrupt in between,
在下一个示例中，
and in next case,
内核可能必须禁用或启用中断，
you know the kernel might actually have to disable or enable interrupts
使代码序列是原子的。
to make basically code sequences atomic.
中断启用和禁用。
So interrupt enable and disable.
稍后我会更详细地谈到，
I'll talk about in a second in more detail
第三关于并发的问题，
and sort of the third sort of concurrency problem
出现在中断处理程序中。
that shows up in the, in interrupt handler.
让我换个说法，
Let me say, let me say differently,
驱动的顶部和底部可以并行运行。
the top of the driver and the bottom of the driver may run in parallel.
比如，在我们的例子中，
So, for example in our example,
shell 会再次调用 write 系统调用，
the shell is going to be called the write system call again,
在打印 $ 之后打印空格，
you know to print the white space after it printed the $
如果你回到驱动的顶部，
and while you may go back into the top level of the driver,
它可能想，
it might want to and may want to
添加这个空格到 UART 的队列中，
add you know, this white space to that queue the the uart actually has,
但同时在另一个 CPU 上，
but at the same time on another CPU,
它可能在处理来自 UART 的中断，
it might actually take interrupt you know for the uart
这也是并行运行的，
and basically also running in parallel
这是相同的代码，查看相同的队列。
and that's sort of roughly the same code and looking at the same queue.
所以这是真的，
And so it's really true
中断处理程序可以并行运行，
that basically the interrupt handler can run in parallel
设备驱动的底部，
at the bottom half of the device driver
可能并行运行在不同的 CPU 上，
may run in parallel on different CPUs,
与驱动程序的顶部位于不同的 CPU 上。
on the different CPU with the top half of the driver.
所以我们必须处理好这个，
So we have to manage that a bit,
而我们管理的方式就是使用锁。
and the way we're going to manage that is using locks.
因为这里有一个共享的数据结构，
Because there's a shared data structure here
我们需要一个缓冲区，
and then we need a buffer
我们要确保缓冲区正确更新，
and we're going to make sure that you know the buffer is updated correctly,
需要确保一次只有一个 CPU
and you need to make sure that only one CPU at a time,
操纵这个特定的缓冲区，
basically manipulates that particular buffer,
我们需要使用锁。
we're going to use locks.
锁将是周三课程的主题，
And locks is going to be the topic of Wednesday's lecture,
我不会讨论太多，
I'm not gonna talk much about it at all,
但是在周三会有很多讨论。
but it will show a big time on Wednesday.
我想关注的是生产者-消费者平行性，
The thing I want to focus on is actually to producer consumer parallelism,
这是一种在驱动程序出现的典型模式，
and this is a typical thing that shows up in drivers
这是非常常见的。
and it's extremely common to see that.
生产者和消费者。
So producer consumer.
这也很简单，
And it's pretty straightforward,
当你看到，驱动程序中有一个缓冲区，
so when you see, you know there's basically a buffer in the driver,
在我们的示例中，我想有 32 个条目，
you know in our case, I think there were 32 entries in it,
从 0 到 31 ，
so zero to three one
并且有两个指针，
and there's two pointers,
有一个读指针和一个写指针。
there's a read pointer and the write pointer.
写指针，读指针，
You know, the write pointer read pointer
如果它们相等，缓冲区就是空的，
if they are equal, you know the buffer is empty
当 shell 写入时，比如使用 putc ，
and so when you know the shell, we do a write, you know putc,
就是把像 $ 这样的字符放到这里，
that basically puts the character like the $ here
并将写指针指向下一条目。
and bumps up the write pointer to the next entry.
这就是生产者的部分，
So that's sort of the producer part
生产者可以继续，
and the producer can keep going,
填满所有这些字符，
you know filling up you know all this characters
直到到达，
until you know it, until hits you know the,
直到如果下一个将达到读指针，
until you know if the next increment would hit the read pointer,
我们知道这个循环缓冲区已满，
we know that this circle buffer is full
在这时，生产者必须停止，
and at that point you know the producer must stop
我们之前在代码中看到了，
and we saw that happening in the, in the code a second ago,
UART 调用 sleep ，
where the uart, basically the uart called sleep
把 shell 放在边上，
and will put this the shell on the side
并运行另一个进程。
and start running another process.
所以中断处理程序 uartinit 或 intr ，
So the interrupt handler, uartinit or intr,
这种情况下，在消费者这边，
in this case at the consumer,
每次都是 uartstart ，
immediately every time when it's a uartstart basically,
当你在中断中，它查看读指针，
when you're in interrupts, it will look at you know the read pointer,
如果读指针在写指针之后，
if the read pointer is behind the write pointer,
写指针已经走远，
so the write pointer already further,
假设这里是空格，
let's say spaces here too, now,
我不知道怎么画空格，但这有一个空格。
I don't know actually how to draw a space, but here's a space.
所以写指针现在可能在这里。
And so the write pointer might now be here.
所以在[]发出之后，
So after the [] being sent,
UART 看到，在写指针后面，
you know the uart sees, you know I'm behind the write pointer,
这意味着得发送下一个。
and that means I got to send the next one.
所以你可以把它看作是，
And so you can think about this as sort of
写指针，读指针在改变写指针，
the write you know pointer, the read pointer is changing the the write pointer
这就是正在发生的事情，
and that's what's going on,
现在可能出现，
now it could be the case,
在某个时候， UART 与写指针保持同步，
that at some point, the uart keeps up with the write pointer
当它们相等时，它知道缓冲区是空的，
and when they're equal and then it knows that the buffer is empty
没什么事情可做。
and there's nothing to do.
这能理解吗？
Does that make sense?
不好意思，这个数据结构对所有核心都是相同的吗？
Sorry, so this data structure is the same for all cores?
好的，让我回到代码上来，
Okay, so let me go back to the code right,
然后是高层级的图片。
then a high-level picture.
让我们回到 UART ，
And let's go back to uart,
所以这个数据结构，
so this data structure,
刚才谈到的就是这个缓冲区。
that we just talked about is this buffer.
这两个指针，写指针和读指针，
And the two pointers you know the write and the read pointer,
是两个索引用来[]。
are these two indexes use in [].
好的?
Okay?
并且这个数据结构在内存中，
And this data structure is in memory,
这里只有一个 RAM ，
and there's only one RAM right
所以，所有核心都可能与这个数据结构并行交互。
and so all the cores might be interacting with this data structure in parallel.
这就是为什么我们需要锁。
That's why we need locks.
好的，我知道了。
Okay I see.
还有一个关于 sleep 的问题，
And rather the question was for sleep,
它怎么知道让 shell 睡觉，
how does it know to make the shell sleep,
比如，那里写入的只有地址。
like what is written there is just the address of.
基本上， sleep 让当前运行的进程进入睡眠状态，
Let me, basically the sleep puts the current process running on the sleep, in a sleep state,
我们下周会讨论它的很多细节。
we'll talk about it in next week or the week after a great amount of detail.
它传入的是，正在等待的东西。
And it passes in the thing that is waiting for.
在这种情况下，
And in this case,
这个地址有一个 channel id ，
that is the address, you know basically has a channel id
或者一种与睡眠程序交互的方式。
or a way of communicating from what actually sleeping on.
在本例中，[] 是 uart_tx_r 的地址。
And so in this case, the [] is the address of uart_tx_r.
并且 start 函数，
And, and the start function,
它需要缓冲区中的空间，
it wants their space again in the buffer,
它会唤醒，
it will wakeup,
使用对应的 wakeup 以及 urat_tx_r ，
call the corresponding call wakeup with the uart_tx_r
表示睡眠在这个地址的任何进程都应该唤醒。
to indicate that any process that actually sleeping on this address should be woken up.
具体是如何实现的，我们稍后会看到。
And how does exactly implemented is something that we'll see a little bit later.
这能理解吗。
So, it makes sense.
所以，这两个调用是相互的， sleep 和 wakeup ，
So these two calls go together, sleep and wakeup,
有时称为条件同步。
sometimes called conditional synchronization.
还有其他问题吗？
Any other questions?
好的。
Okay.
很好。
Good.
让我们看看。
Let's, let's see.
所以，这就是打印 $ 的全部故事，
So that there's basically the whole story for printing $
正如你所看到的，它涉及到很多部分，
and as you can see it's actually quite involved a lot of pieces
（这些部分）一起将 $ 发送到 console 。
that you know working together to actually get this $ out to the console.
类似的事情也发生在读取端，
And something similar basically happens on the read side,
在某个时候， shell 打印 $ 和空格，
so at some point shell has printed the both the $ and the white space,
然后调用 read 读取来自键盘的输入，
and then will call read to basically read input from the keyboard,
所以现在我们看看发生了什么，
so now we wanted to see what happens,
当它发生时，
when that happening,
这也是从 file 开始的。
so that starts basically in the with file again.
所以现在有一个读系统调用，
So now there's a read system call,
如果从 console 上读，
if it's you know reading from the console,
它会调用 fileread ，
it will calls, it will actually of course fileread,
抱歉，不是 write 。
sorry not write.
如果它是设备，在本例中是 console ，
If it's the device which in this case, the case is a console,
然后，我们调用该设备的读方法，
then we call the read method for that device,
这在 console.c 中，
and that is in console.c
所以，我们调用 consoleread 。
and so we're going to, consoleread is being called.
基本上它与 UART 有相同的结构，
And basically it has the same structure as uart,
在顶部有一个环形缓冲区。
you know there's a circular buffer on the top.
这就是它， INPUT_BUF ，有 128 个字符，
Here it is, it's INPUT_BUF [] the 128 characters in it
基本上是相同的游戏，
and basically it's the same game,
是生产者-消费者并行性，
its producer consumer parallelism,
但是，在这种情况下， shell 是消费者，
but in this case, the shell is the consumer, right,
它从缓冲区中读取字符。
it actually is reading you know characters off the buffer.
键盘是生产者，
And the keyboard is the producer,
它将字符放入缓冲区。
it takes the characters into the buffer.
所以，让我们回到 consoleread ，
And so you know, let's go back to consoleread,
如果什么都没有，
if there's nothing,
如果读指针，读索引和写索引相同，
if the read pointer where to read index and write index are the same,
缓冲区是空的，
you know the buffer is empty
它又回到睡眠状态。
and it goes back to sleep again.
所以，在打印 $ 之后，
And so, so after it's printed dollar [],
shell 会去睡眠，
the shell is go to sleep,
内核将 shell 置于睡眠状态，直到字符进入。
kernel put the shell sleep until character comes in.
在某一时刻，用户输入 l ，
And so at some point, let's say user types in l,
ls 的第一个字符，
you know the first character from ls on the keyboard,
这将导致 l 发送到电路板上的 UART 芯片，
that will calls, you know, the l to be sent into the uart chip on the on the board,
它将通过 PLIC 到某个核心，
that will be round through the plic to some core,
核心将接受中断，到 devintr ，
that core will take the interrupt that will go to devintr,
devintr ，我们会看到 UART 中断是如何进行的，
the devintr we'll see how that goes uart interrupt
它将调用我们刚才看到的函数。
and it will call the function that we looked at a second ago.
它会回到底部，
It goes back to the bottom,
我自己迷惑了一下的地方，
where I got confused myself for a second,
所以在这种情况下，它会写，
so in this case, you know it will write,
它会从 UART 设备获取字符，
it will get a character from the device from uart device
获得字符 l ，
that will get the character l
使用字符 l 调用 consoleintr 函数，
and will call the consoleintr function using the character l,
这样我们就可以回到 console 。
so we can go back to console.
consoleintr 得到那个字符，
And consoleintr does gets the character,
所以现在我们有一个 l ，
so now we have an l,
它是控制 P ，打印进程列表，
it's a control P, you know actually printing list, in the process list,
实现控制 H 和 控制 U ，
implements control H and control U,
用来回退和控制别的东西。
to do backspace and control whatever.
但是，在所有其他情况下，
But in all other cases,
基本上所做的是，
basically what it does,
通过将字符打印到 console 将其回显给用户。
it echoes the character back to the user by printing it to the console.
然后它将字符放入缓冲区，
And then it basically sticks the character into the buffer,
并唤醒等待缓冲区的进程，
so that and wakeup you know the process that's waiting for the buffer,
如果有进程在等待。
if there's a process waiting.
如果它达到换行，并且有进程等待，
If it has hit newline and there's a process waiting,
它会唤醒等待进程，
it will wake up the waiting process,
然后等待进程将从缓冲区中读取字符。
and then the waiting process will read you know the characters out of the buffer.
这里我们又看到了这种解耦，
Okay, so here again we see this sort of decoupling
在生产者和消费者之间使用缓冲区，
using a buffer between the consumer and the producer,
以便生产者消费者可以并行运行，
so that the producer consumer can run in parallel,
以各自的速度独立运行，
independent each on their own speed,
如果一个跑得很快，
and if one goes very fast,
无论缓冲区是空，还是满，
you know either buffer will be empty or full,
就阻塞并等待对方追赶上来。
and then block wait until the other guy catch up.
这个，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about this?
好的。
Okay.
好的，我想再谈一件事。
Okay, I wanna talk basically about one more thing.
那就是。
In that is.
我主要谈论中断的发展，
You know I'm mostly talking a little bit about sort of interrupt evolution,
比如，过去几十年发生的事情。
like what has happened over the last decades.
所以，对于处理器来说，中断曾经是相当快的，
So the interrupts used to be relative to processor reasonable fast,
特别是在，
in particular in the,
曾经很快。
used to be fast.
所以，在最初的 Unix 被开发的时候，
So in times the original Unix was developed,
就是这种情况，
you know that was the case
意味着硬件非常简单。
and that basically meant that the hardware is very simple.
因为，如果有什么重要的工作要做，
Because you know if any really serious work needs to be done,
我们可以直接中断处理器，
[] we could just interrupt the processor
处理器会做这些工作，
and the processor would do it on the work
所以硬件本身是非常直接的。
and so hardware itself could be reasonable straight forward.
现在，与处理器相比，中断比较慢，
Now, interrupts are slow compared to the processor,
你可以看到，
you can see that right,
因为中断处理程序需要保存寄存器，
because the interrupt handler, it needs to save to registers,
它需要接受中断，
it needs to take the interrupt,
有几个预算指令，
so there's a couple you know a small budget instructions
它们只用来服务于中断。
that are just being used to actually serve the interrupt.
因此如果设备产生高速中断，
And so if device generates interrupts the high speed,
处理器很难跟上。
you know then the processor going to have a tough time keeping up.
所以，你看今天的设备，
And so you look at today's devices,
硬件或设备有更多的工作要做，
basically the hardware or the device there's a lot more work,
设备本身有很多工作要做，
and so basically there's a bunch of work actually on the device itself,
在实际生成中断之前。
before actually generating an interrupt.
所以，为了避免过多地中断处理器，
And so, and just to avoid interrupting the processor too much,
现在，如果你有一个高性能设备，
now, if you really have a high performance device,
比如，你有千兆以太网，
like say you have gigabytes gigabits Ethernet,
这块网卡使用很多小包，
and you know that card is use a lot of small packages packets,
那么网卡可以产生，
then you know you can actually generate or Ethernet itself could generate
大约每秒 150 万个包，
about one five or 1.5 million packets per second,
对于最小的 64 字节以太网包，
for minimum of like 64 byte Ethernet package,
你粗略计算一下，
you do a math roughly out to,
每秒生成 150 万个包，你可以接收。
basically you generated 1.5 million packets per second you could receive.
所以，这意味着如果你对每个包中断，
And so that basically means you know one interrupt, if you did it for every packet,
那就是一微秒一个中断
per microsecond.
事实上，略高于，
In fact, a little more than,
略低于，
a little less than,
略高于，
a little bit more than,
所以，考虑如果一微秒一个中断，
so basically one way to think about if one interrupt microsecond,
内核中的操作，
there's basically the operations in a kernel,
有一微秒的预算指令来处理这个包，
basically has a budget of like one microsecond instructions to actually process that packet,
实际上是 150 万，
in fact it's 1.5 million,
这比一微秒的预算要少一点。
such a little bit less than a budget of a microsecond.
你可以计算出有多少条指令，
And you can compute how many instructions that is,
不会有那么多，
there's not gonna be that much
所以在这种情况下，
and so in that case,
我们需要有一个不同的计划，
you know we need to have a different plan,
那么你怎么处理这些中断包，
so what do you do with the packets or interrupt you know packets
以超过处理器速度进来的包。
are coming in so fast that processor really can't keep up.
对于快速设备的解决方案是，
And the solution to that is to with fast devices is
有时称为轮询。
actually sometimes uses called polling.
不是写入中断，
And, instead of writing interrupts,
CPU 也可以，
you know what the CPU also could do is
只是读取控制寄存器，
just keep reading that control register
查看那里是否有一个字节，
and to see if there's a byte there,
比如在 UART 寄存器中，
like in uart register,
我们只是不停读取 LHR 寄存器，
we just keep reading that LHR register
只是检查那里是否有一个字节。
and just check if there's a byte there.
说到底，这是 CPU 旋转，
In basically, would you know what this boils down to is that the CPU you know spins,
它在设备上旋转，
it spins on the device,
直到设备有输入，有数据。
you know until device has input, has data.
这会浪费 CPU 周期，
And you know this waste CPU cycles right,
因为我们一遍又一遍地检查那个寄存器，
because while we're checking that register over and over and over again
看它是否是数据，
to see if they're actually any data,
我们没有使用这些周期来运行另一个应用程序，
you know we're not using those cycles to run another application right
我们之前看到的，
and you know before what you're seeing is that
如果没有任何东西，内核会让 shell 睡眠，
if there's nothing there, basically the kernel push the shell to sleep,
以便另一个应用程序可以运行。
so that another application could run.
但是如果我们做轮询，那就不会发生了，
But if we do polling, then that wouldn't happen,
现在，对于速度慢的设备，
now for a slow device,
你当然希望不是永远旋转，
you clearly want you know not spin forever
直到设备来做它的工作，
until device finally gets around to actually doing its work,
我们想从 shell 切换出去，
we really like to basically switch out the shell
并运行其他东西。
and so that we can run something else.
但如果设备速度非常快，
But if the device is extremely fast,
则中断的开销很高，
then the overhead of the interrupt features high
我们最好还是轮询设备，
and you know we're better off actually waiting basically polling the device,
因为我们很快就会成功。
because very quickly we're going to get success.
但是，如果设备比较慢，又浪费 CPU 。
And so if, but so if waste CPU, if device slow.
但是如果设备速度很快，
But you know, but if devices fast,
它节省了保存时间，
it saves save saving or storing,
节省了 entry 和 exit 成本。
which saves the all entry entry and exit costs.
所以，比如高性能网卡，
And so for example, high performing network card,
如果有一连串包进来，
you know, will you know if it's a stream of packets coming in
将使用轮询。
and actually will use polling.
更多的复杂驱动，
And you know more and the most sophisticated drivers
它们会动态切换地在轮询和中断之间切换。
basically they dynamically switch, switch between polling and interrupts.
好的。
Okay.
有什么问题吗？
Any questions?
我的安排时间快到了。
Close to my, my time budget is up.
有什么剩下的问题吗？
Any your remaining questions?
好的，那我们周三见，
Okay, good, then I'll see you on Wednesday
在周三，我们将继续并发并行的故事，
and basically Wednesday, we're going to continue the story of concurrency parallelism,
我们将看到一些机制管理并行，
we're gonna see some mechanisms to actually manage the parallelism
确保共享数据结构正确获取它们的数据。
to make sure that shared data structures, get them data correctly.
那么，周三见。
So, see you on Wednesday.
抱歉，我想找出我的问题在哪里，
Oh, I'm sorry, I just I was trying to find where my question was,
因为我把它弄丢了，
because I lost it,
我的问题是，
my question was in the,
所以我看到 uartinit 只被调用了一次，
so I saw it, uartinit is just being called once,
这是为什么只有一个缓冲区供所有核心共享的原因吗？
is that why there's just one buffer for all the cores to share together.
好的，这里只有一个 UART 设备。
Well, there's always the only one uart device.
缓冲区对应于 UART 设备，
Buffer corresponds you know to the one uart device
实际上是由多个核心共享的。
actually is being shared between all the cores.
它可能是在不同核心上运行的多个进程，
You know like it might be multiple processes running on different cores,
都在试图打印到控制台。
all trying to print to the console.
好的，我明白了，
Okay I see,
是的，有道理。
oh yeah, makes sense makes sense.
所以，只有一个队列会使用 UART 执行任务。
So like only one queue will do stuff with uart to the time.
是的，这有点复杂，
Yeah, well you know it's slightly complicated,
但是假设有多个人在写，
but let's look, like, so let's say there's multiple guys writing,
只需做一次实验就行了。
just afford as one [experiment], correct.
我们看到有多个，
And and what we see there are multiple,
让我。
let me actually.
这里是 uartputc ，
So here uartputc,
你看到的第一件事是它需要一个锁。
the first thing you see is actually it actually requires a lock.
多个核心正在将一个字符放入缓冲区，
So the multiple cores are trying to put a character into the buffer
它们中的一个获得锁，
and one of them is going to get the lock
其他都不会获得锁，
and none of the others are going to lock,
所以那个获得锁的 CPU ，
so that one guy you know the one CPU that actually got the lock, required to lock successfully,
可以查看写指针，
is able to go and look at the write pointer
把字符放入其中，
and stick character in it possible
否则去睡眠。
and otherwise go to sleep.
如果它完成了，就可以解锁，
And you know and then if it's done, you know releases the lock,
然后下一个核心可以进入，
and then the next you know core can go in
获取锁并做它的工作。
and acquire the lock and do its work.
所以，这个锁会序列化对 UART 的并发访问。
So this lock will serialize the concurrent accesses to the uart.
理解了，是的，谢谢。
That makes sense, yeah, thank you.
好的，星期三我们将详细讨论锁的问题。
Well, on Wednesday, we'll talk in detail about locks.
谢谢。
Thank you.
还有什么问题吗？
Any further questions?
我有个问题。
I have a question.
我知道我们要在中断使用锁，
So, as far as I understand why we need the lock inside the interrupted,
因为只有一个控制台，
because we there's only one console
而有多个核心。
and they could multiple cores, right.
你是说哪里的锁。
You mean the where is the lock, where.
我想是这样的，
I think so right,
因为通常我们不想在中断内部使用锁。
because usually we don't want to lock things inside interrupts right.
是的，你通过电子邮件问了这个问题。
Yeah you asked this question by email.
是的。
Yeah.
是的，问题是，
Yes, well the issue is,
正如前面提到的，
that the as mentioned earlier,
底部的中断处理可以和顶部的并行运行。
the bottom half interrupt handler could run in parallel with the top half.
所以，一个核心可能正在执行 uartputc ，
And so one core could be doing uartputc
而另一个核心可能正在运行 uartintr ，
and another core could be running uartintr,
我们要确保它们在某种程度上，
we got to make sure that they sort of,
不会纠缠在一起，
don't get tangled up together,
让它们串行，
that they serialized correctly
锁确保了它们被序列化。
and the lock basically ensures that they get serialized.
好的，有道理，
Okay, that makes sense,
但是否意味着有时候
but that does mean that sometimes
所有的核心都可能在等待
like all cores could potentially be waiting for
其中的一个处理这件事。
one of them to be handling this, right.
是的。
Yeah.
是，因为中断必须等待，
Yeah, because the interrupt has to wait
没有什么事情可以调度了。
and then nothing else can get scheduled.
一些其他进程可能在运行，
Well, presumably some other process maybe running,
它不是，这不是死锁，
it's unlikely, there's no deadlock,
好的，有死锁的风险，但不是这个，
okay, there is a risk of deadlock, but not this one,
那个我们将在周三谈论。
that we'll talk about on Wednesday.
但是，它的大概意思是，
But in the, presumably, what this means
如果有多个调用 uartputc ，
like if there's multiple guys called uartputc,
缓冲区已满，
in the buffer full,
然后在某个时刻，这个中断会释放锁。
then some point, this interrupt they actually will release the lock.
让我们回到 uartputc ，
So, for example let's go back to uartputc,
实际上发生的事情是，
what actually what happened correct is that,
它们会调用 sleep ，
they will call sleep,
而 sleep 使用那个锁作为参数，
and sleep actually takes the locks in argument
我们后面会知道为什么，
and we'll see later why,
但是在内部，在 sleep 将进程睡眠之前，
but internally before sleep actually puts the process definitely to sleep
它会释放锁。
and will release the lock.
哦，我明白了，
Oh, I see,
所以是调用 sleep 带上锁参数，
so basically you call sleep with the lock
然后意味着可以在睡眠的时候释放锁，
and then that means okay release the lock while you sleep,
让其他进程去做。
so someone else does it.
好的，有意思。
Okay interesting.
是的。
Yeah.
然后，当从 sleep 返回，
And then when you return from sleep,
再次获取，好的。
you just reacquire, okay.
重新获得锁。
To get lock back.
对，是的，有道理。
Right, right, yeah that make sence.
sleep 也有单独的故事，
And the sleep has a seperate story,
我们将在一周或两周后讨论这个。
that we'll talk about in a week or two weeks.
有道理，是的，是的，
That makes sense, yeah yeah,
所以我想，
so I guess,
所以我想这对我来说不是很清楚，
so I guess that wasn't that clear to me
是不是所有的 CPU 都会被中断，
do all CPUs get interrupted,
当有人通过 UART 发送东西的时候。
when somebody like send something through uart.
不，要看情况，
No, well depends,
这取决于你怎么对 PLIC 编程，
it depends on how you program the plic,
xv6 对 PLIC 的编程方式是只有一个 CPU ，
the way xv6 program the plic is that only one CPU,
所有的 CPU 都可能被中断，但是。
all CPU might get interrupted, but.
好的。
Okay.
只有一个去处理中断。
One is going to clean the interrupt.
好的。
Okay.
如果你回到 PLIC ，
If you go back to the plic,
当你获得中断，会调用 plic_claim ，
you know when you get interrupted, you call this plic_claim
那个 CPU 会得到，
and that CPU that particular core gonna get the,
它会得到 IRQ ，
it's going to get the the IRQ
然后 PLIC 会记住，
and then basically the plic will remember,
那个 IRQ 正在处理，
that IRQ is now being served
不会把它给其他任何人。
and won't give it to anybody else.
我明白了，好的，
I see, okay,
所以，它们中的一个会获得它，随机的还是别的。
so just one of them will get it randomly or no.
你可以编程 PLIC ，
You can program to plic,
比如编程到一个 CPU 。
you know say maybe program to one CPU.
我明白了。
Oh I see.
PLIC。
Plic.
我明白了，
I see, I see,
所以在 PLIC 里面是相关的代码，
so inside the, yeah inside the plic is the code
来决定打扰谁。
that actually decides on who to bother.
是的， PLIC 是一个[]，
Yeah, the plic a [],
我想 PLIC 里面没有代码。
there's no code in the plic, I think.
是啊，好的。
Yeah right, okay, okay I was.
CPU 编程。
CPU program.
我是，是的，好的。
I was, yeah great, okay.
是的，我想说 PLIC 代码在哪里运行，
Yeah, I was just gonna say where does the plic code run,
但是，是的，它不是代码，而是硬件，
but yeah it's not code, it's hardware.
好的，理解了。
Okay that makes sense.
谢谢，星期三见。
Alright, thanks, I'll see you on Wednesday.
好的。
Yeah.
我有个问题，
So I got a question,
与同时运行多个核心的想法有关。
kind of related to the thinking about multiple cores running at the same time.
我想起其中一个实验，
So I think I recalling one of the labs
在 prime 问题中，
with say the prime question
我们看到实际上是交错输出，
we saw that print actually like interleaves output [],
是不是因为锁只是在 putc ，
is that because the locks are only around like the putc,
但是来自多个核心的 putc 调用可以交错，
but the putc calls from multiple cores could interleave,
意味着单个 print[] 不能保证是原子的。
meaning that a single print [] is not guaranteed to be atomic.
你是对的。
You got it.
好的，理解了。
Okay, that makes sense.
好的，谢谢。
Alright, thank you.
不用谢。
You're welcome.
我有一个简短的问题，
I have a quick question,
我记得阅读材料里有，
so I remember reading in the like,
阅读材料表示计时器中断是在机器模式下处理的，
the reading said something about the timer interrupts being handled in machine mode
我想知道是在哪里处理的，
and I was wondering where that was handled
当我们做 traps 实验时，
when we were doing the traps lab,
比如，在 traps 实验中，在哪里切换到机器模式，
like where the switch to machine mode was happening during the traps lab
然后我们在做什么。
and then what we were doing.
好的，好问题，
Yeah, okay great question,
你知道。
so you know the.
所以我调出代码，
So I I'm pulling up the code,
所以如果你查看 start ，
so if you look at your start correctly,
有一个 start 运行在 M 模式，
there's a start runs in M mode
当机器启动时的开始时间，
at the beginning of time when the machine boots,
并且它对计时器检查进行编程，
and it programs the timer check,
这是 timerinit
and so here's timerinit
而 timerinit 对 CLINT 进行编程，
and timerinit basically programs the plic the clint,
这是本地中断，
which is the local interrupt,
在时钟中断发生时生成中断，
to generate interrupts when the clock interrupt happens
这可能是这里最重要的函数，
and basically here's probably the most important function here,
它将机器模式的 trap 处理函数设置为这个 timervec 函数，这个名为timervec的函数，
it sets the machine mode trap handler to this function called timervec,
那是由汇编编写的。
that's written assembly.
当计时器中断发生时，
And when the timer interrupt happens,
这个函数会被调用。
that function is being called.
所以，当内核在用户模式或管理模式下运行时，
And so when your kernel running user mode or in supervisor mode
CLINT 生成一个中断到达这一行，
and clint generates an interrupt [reach] the line
它将切换到机器模式，
and it will switch to machine mode
并且调用这个函数 timervec ，
and call this function timervec,
基本上与管理模式和用户模式中看到的相同。
in same way basically as almost equivalent to what we've seen for supervisor mode and user mode.
好的？
Okay?
是的。
Sure.
然后，如果你看一下 kernelvec.S 。
And then if you look in kernelvec.S.
我们看了很多次 kernelvec ，
We looked at kernelvec a lot right,
我的意思是那个函数，
I mean that stuff function
看看它是否保存了很多东西。
to see if it stores a lot.
这是 timervec ，
And here's timervec,
它基本上是类似的想法，
it's basically the same sort of type of idea,
我们看看它是一些寄存器，
let's see it's a couple registers,
让它可以完成工作，
so that it can do its job
它做的就是在这里编写六行代码，
and the only job it does actually these sort of six lines of code here,
或者五行，七行代码，
or whatever five seven lines of code
它所做的就是对 CLINT 重新编程，
and basically what it does you know re-programs the clint
以生成未来的中断，
to generate future interrupts
然后向管理程序发出软件中断，
and then basically raises a software interrupt to the supervisor,
所以，它将进入管理者模式。
so that goes to supervisor mode.
好吧。
Okay.
然后，在 mret 的时候，
So then at the point at mret,
mret ，比如内核使用计时器中断，
mret, let's say the kernel was interrupted during a timer chip with a timer chip,
它进入机器模式，
so it went to machine mode,
然后 mret 从机器模式返回到管理者模式，
mret then returned from machine mode back to supervisor mode, right,
如果中断启用了管理者模式，
and if the interrupt enabled supervisor mode,
这个时刻，可能产生管理者软件中断。
at that point, maybe the supervisor, in the supervisor software interrupt will be generated.
哦，好的。
Oh, okay.
现在，内核也会做同样的事情，
And now basically the kernel will do the same thing,
转到 kernelvec ，
basically will go to kernelvec,
保存恢复所有寄存器，
you know save restore all the registers
然后转到内核 trap ，
and and then go to a kernel trap
内核 trap 会看到那是计时器中断。
and the kernel trap will see aha, that was the timer interrupt.
我明白了，
I see,
那么切换到机器模式是在哪一点，
and so what was the point of switching to machine mode in the first place
它到底做了什么。
at like what exactly does it do.
我不知道在哪一点，
I don't know what the point is,
这是硬件工作。
this is hardware works.
好的，知道了。
Okay, gotcha.
实际上做得更多一点，
Actually do a little bit more,
是的，这里有一些原因，
yeah yeah yeah, there are some reasons
我想为什么在机器模式使用计时器，
I think why use a timer chip exposed to machine mode,
但从我们的角度来看，
but from our perspective,
这很好，
you know would be great,
如果我们能把定时器中断交给管理者模式，
if we could have delegated the timer interrupt [] to supervisor mode
而不用处理定时器模式，
and never had to deal with timer mode,
但是，对这个特殊的芯片是不起作用的。
but you know that doesn't work for this particular chip.
好的，有道理，非常感谢。
Okay, that makes sense, thank you so much.
不用谢。
You're welcome.
哦，我有一个关于这部分的跟进问题。
Oh, I actually have a follow-up on this part of.
请继续你的问题。
So keep ask your questions.
好的。
Yeah.
我看到它分配了 32 个 uint64 ，
I saw that it allocates 32 uint64,
但是它似乎只用了四个或三个，
but it only seems to be using four, no three of them, right.
嗯。
Um.
在 start.c 中。
In start.c, it.
在 scratch ，
At scratch,
是的，我想它分配的比需要的多，
yeah I guess it allocates more than is necessary,
32 个暂存区域，
scratches thirty-two scratch area,
原因是，
the reason,
对于每一个 CPU ，
so, so for every CPU correct,
必须有一些暂存空间，
there has to be some scratch space
我想那里有三个或类似的 CPU ，
and there I guess we have three or something like that CPUs,
所以多分配一点，
so basically allocates a little bit too much,
但不会[]分配太多。
but there's no [] allocating too much.
好的，比如，它只用 scratch[0] scratch[1] scratch[1] ，
Okay, okay, it's like it only uses scratch zero scratch one scratch two.
不，我想是使用 3 ，
No, you know [uses] three, I guess,
从 0 到 3 ，是四个，
so as zero to three, that's four,
4 和 5 是六个，
four or five current six,
所以是六个整数，
so it's six integers
我想，我们可以运行四个 CPU ，
and I guess, we have we're running we could run with four CPUs,
但我们运行了三个，
but we're running with three,
但我们可以运行四个。
but we could run four.
所以 6 乘以 24 ，
So six times four twenty four,
我想肯定分配了太多内存。
I guess you know the, we definitely allocating too much memory.
我不记得，不久前我想过这件事，
I don't remember I thought about this a while back ago
我也记不清 32 是从哪里来的了。
and I don't remember exactly where 32 came from.
所以，我们需要再检查一遍。
So we need double check.
你可以重建它。
So you can reconstruct it.
哦，是的，保存恢复，都是 8 字节的。
Oh yeah, save restore, they all they all eight bytes, right.
是的。
Yeah.
还有，它。
And it.
好的，我晚点给你说，
Okay, let me get back to you,
我现在想不起来了，
I can't recall right at the top my head
为什么是这样的。
you know why it is the way it is.
好的，有道理，非常感谢。
Okay, makes sense, thank you so much.
不客气，问得好。
You're welcome, good questions.
谢谢。
Thank you.